<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The middle-way in one paper of election &amp; redemption, with indifferency between the Arminian &amp; Calvinist / by Jo. H.</title>
            <author>Humfrey, John, 1621-1719.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1673</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 109 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 22 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A45138</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H3689</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R20384</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12224567</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12224567</idno>
            <idno type="VID">56460</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A45138)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 56460)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 919:34)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The middle-way in one paper of election &amp; redemption, with indifferency between the Arminian &amp; Calvinist / by Jo. H.</title>
                  <author>Humfrey, John, 1621-1719.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 40, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for L. Parkhurst ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1673.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Written by John Humfrey.  Cf. Wing.</note>
                  <note>Advertisement: p. [1] at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the University of Illinois (Urbana-Champaign Campus). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Election (Theology) --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Redemption --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Predestination --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:56460:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:56460:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Middle-Way In One Paper of ELECTION &amp; REDEMPTION.</p>
            <p>With Indifferency between the <hi>ARMINIAN</hi> &amp; <hi>CALVINIST.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> J H</p>
            <q>
               <p>Doing nothing by Partiality.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1 Tim. 5.21.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>T. Parkhurſt,</hi> at the Three Bibles in <hi>Cheap-ſide.</hi> 1673.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:56460:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:56460:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>OF</hi> Election, <hi>or</hi> Predeſtination.</head>
               <p>THe deſigne of theſe Papers is to offer to ſuch as will <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider,</hi> and can tend to <hi>receive,</hi> or <hi>cultivate</hi> what is offered, ſome Notices of truth which lye upon my mind about ſeverall matters, that, by the <hi>Communication</hi> of the <hi>little</hi> light I have, I may fetch in <hi>more</hi> to my own underſtanding from <hi>others:</hi> and alſo by the <hi>Partiality</hi> that appeares ſo often in the doctrine of the <hi>Orthodox,</hi> I may promote ſome generall kind of condeſcenſion in <hi>all perſons</hi> to a more favourable opinion of one another: the proper conſciouſneſs of our own moſt miſerable palpable blindneſs in moſt things, and ſeveral points of Religion, (wherein many times we are indeed but the more <hi>blind,</hi> becauſe wee think we <hi>ſee</hi>), being enough methinks to make every mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall, even with ſhame and confuſion, to be ready either to have a little <hi>higher</hi> eſtimation of his Brother that differ from him, or a little <hi>leſs</hi> indignation at any ſuch difference, or diſtance in his way and judgment.</p>
               <p>I will begin with theſe heads. Of Election, and of Redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p>It is the generall opinion of Divines, that God from all eternity fore knows all things, and, That, there are a certain number
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:56460:3"/>of perſons determined by Him that ſhall be infallibly brought to glory. For declaring this Decree, they do go ſeverall wayes. In the generall, they may be reduced to two: the way of <hi>Abſolute;</hi> and the way of <hi>Conditionall</hi> Election. Of either way there are two ſorts. In the Conditional way; The firſt ſort do conceive, that God foreſees who they be that will <hi>live</hi> godlily and keep his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements, and them he chooſes to ſalvation; while thoſe he foreſees will be wicked, he decrees to damnation. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nde A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtolus</hi> (ſay they). <hi>Quos praeſcivit, hos &amp; praedeſtinavit. From whence the Apoſtle Whom he did foreknow, them he alſo did praedeſtinate.</hi> The ſecond ſort, perceiving this to be contrary to Scripture, with makes Election to be of <hi>grace</hi> &amp; not of <hi>works,</hi> do ſay thus: That God foreſees who they be will <hi>beleeve,</hi> and ſo chooſing them as being in Chriſt through faith, decrees to give them grace, which will lead them to ſalvation: and thoſe that he foreſees will not believe, he decrees to leave them, as out of Chriſt, to Condemnation. <hi>Non elegit Deus opera cujuſque in praeſcientia quoe ipſe daturus eſt; ſed fidem elegit in praeſcientia, ut, quem ſibi crediturum praeſcivit, Ipſum elegerit ut Spiritum ſanctum daret, ut bona operando etiam vitam aeternam conſequerentur. God did not chooſe the works of any in his foreſight which himſelf was to give, but he choſe faith in his foreſight, that, whom he foreknew would beleeve, he might chooſe them, to give the holy Spirit unto; that by doing good works they might obtain eternall ſalvation.</hi> Auguſtine, <hi>in libro expoſitionis quarundum propoſitionum ex epiſtola ad Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manos.</hi> Again, <hi>Quos Deus ſuos fidei opere futuros eſſe praenovit, hos praedeſtin<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>avit ad gloriam. Thoſe who God foreknew would be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come his through their beleeving, he elected unto glory. De prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtinatione Dei.</hi> c. 5. The former opinion, is the way of the <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lagian;</hi> the latter, of the <hi>Arminian.</hi> Which yet I ſet not down af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the more ſubtle times of <hi>Arminius</hi> himſelf, but thoſe of <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine</hi> according to theſe cited paſſages; the one of which he af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards expreſly retracted; and the book it ſelf out of which I fetch the other, I beleeve either to be ſpurious, or to have got abroad from him unawares, before he had reveiwed it. The Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodox therefore, ſuch as we account the Synod of <hi>Dort,</hi> do declare for the <hi>Abſolute</hi> way, in oppoſition to both theſe. To wit, that God without conſideration either of mans <hi>faith,</hi> or good <hi>works,</hi> but
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:56460:3"/>meerly according to <hi>the counſell of his own will,</hi> not rendring his reaſon to us, hath determined to give that grace to ſome perſons whereby they ſhall effectually be ſaved: and to leave others to the freedome of their own wills, that they may be judged at the laſt Day according to their deſerts. In this way, there are like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe two ſorts of Doctors. The one teach, that God looks on men without any conſideration of ſin at all, in their <hi>ſtate before the Fall,</hi> in this decree of his grace to ſome, and not to others: The other teach, that God looks indeed on men all alike without conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>deſert,</hi> but not without conſideration of <hi>ſin,</hi> to wit in their <hi>faln eſtate;</hi> and ſo decrees his mercy to ſome, and juſtice to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. Note here, that our Divines of the former ſort do not ſay, that, God decrees damnation to any without conſideration of ſin (nor ſalvation indeed without conſideration of faith and repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance): but, Decree's the giving or not giving ſaving grace to keep them from ſin and damnation, to whom he pleaſes, without any conſideration in man whatſoever. For, Predeſtination, ſay they, being an immanent and eternall act of the Divine under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding &amp; will, cannot be conceived as dependent upon any fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeen temporall acts of mans free-will. Note alſo, that St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> who was the firſt ſet up for the <hi>Abſolute</hi> way, and yet not till his latter writings, doth declare for the ſecond ſort of this way. <hi>Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teri autem ubi niſi in maſſa perditionis juſto divino judicio relin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quantur? The reſt that are not elect, are left according to Gods juſt judgment, in the maſſe of thoſe that are faln, unto perdition. De bono perſeverantiae.</hi> c. 14. The one of theſe opinions is called the <hi>Supralapſarian</hi> doctrine: the other, the <hi>Sublapſarian.</hi> Which are names indeed may make a rumbling to many that know not what they ſignify, but ſo long as they come into one and the ſame <hi>Conſequent,</hi> which alone is to be regarded, the difference is not of moment to diſturb any.</p>
               <p>And what is the <hi>Conſequent</hi> then of theſe Doctrines, which is fit to be enquired? The <hi>Conſequent</hi> of the firſt doctrine, that Election is <hi>ex praeviſis operibus, of works foreſeen,</hi> muſt be this, that the good life or good works of men therefore do ariſe from their own free wills, and that the grace of God is given according to their merits. This was the main opinion doubtleſs which the Church condemned in <hi>Pelagius.</hi> From whence indeed thoſe two
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:56460:4"/>other followed, that, Man may therefore chooſe whether he will ever commit any ſin; and, That he muſt be free from original cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption. <hi>Tria ſunt quae maxime adverſus eos catholica defendit eccleſia, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>num eſt, Gratiam Dei non ſecundum merita dari, quoniam Dei dona ſunt. Alterum eſt, in quantacunque juſtitia ſine qualibuſcun<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> peccatis neminem vivere. Tertium eſt, naſci homines peccato primi homnis obnoxios. There are three things eſpecially which the Catholick Church defends againſt the Pelagians: One is, that the Grace of God is not given according to mans merit: Ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is, that there is no man, how great ſoever his righteouſneſs be, that lives without ſome ſins. The third is, that men are born liable to the guilt of Adams firſt tranſgreſſion.</hi> De bon. perſev. c. 2. The conſequent of the ſecond opinion, that Election is <hi>ex praeviſa fide of fore-ſeen faith,</hi> is, That although our <hi>good works</hi> are indeed the fruit onely o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Gods Spirit, and to be aſcribed to Gods grace; yet muſt our <hi>frith,</hi> upon which the Spirit or this grace is given, or by which it is impetrated, as that Father ſpeaks, be both in our <hi>own power</hi> and from our <hi>own will;</hi> as being that, and that alone in man, that <hi>makes the difference</hi> between one and another; or the reaſon why God ſhould chooſe ſuch a one to give him his grace, and paſs by the other. And this <hi>doctrine,</hi> with the <hi>Conſequent</hi> of it, muſt be acknowledged to be St. <hi>Auguſtine's</hi> in his firſt writings, which he choſe no doubt as the moſt moderate then in the Church, which (as we may judg by <hi>Proſper,</hi> and <hi>Hilary's</hi> Epiſtles to him) was never uſed to define election otherwiſe than <hi>ſecundum praeſcientiam, according to foreknowledg,</hi> till his dayes. And this was the reaſon that thoſe of <hi>Marſilia</hi> (<hi>ad quorum authoritatem non ſumus pares,</hi> ſayes one of thoſe Epiſtles, <hi>quia multum nos et vitae meritis an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tecellunt &amp; ſacerdotis honore</hi>) were ſo offended at that Father for his change. And from hence does <hi>Arminius</hi> profeſſe ſome-where, <hi>Non ſtamus Auguſtino, We ſtand not with Auguſtine:</hi> for which this alſo, as I remember, is his reaſon. <hi>Quia ſibi ipſe non ſtetit, becauſe he ſtood not to himſelf.</hi> The Conſequent of the other two doctrines which belong to <hi>Abſolute</hi> election, and come in this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect, I have ſaid, bat to the <hi>ſame,</hi> is, on the contrary hand, That neither our <hi>good works,</hi> nor our <hi>faith</hi> it ſelf, nor indeed any good that is in man, is of our ſelves but of the operation of God, or of his Spirit, who does at firſt excite our wills to Faith and a holy
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:56460:4"/>life, &amp; by his continual aſſiſtance carry us on in perſeverance unto the end, that we may be ſaved; ſo that, the whole buſineſs: of our ſalvation firſt and laſt muſt be aſcribed to Him alone. And if any ask the reaſon then why he gives not the ſame grace to others as to his Elect, he ſhall find theſe words ſtill in St. <hi>Auguſtine's</hi> mouth. <hi>And who art thou that replieſt aga<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nſt God? May he not do what he will with his owne? Hath not the Potter power over his clay. O the depth of the knowledge and wiſdome of God, how unſearchable are his judgments, and his wayes paſt finding out!</hi> It were but jniury to quote a ſentence or two out of the Father for this, which is the deſigned contents of ſeverall of his laſt books. See <hi>de Praedeſtinatione &amp; gratia. De correptione &amp; gratia. De praedeſtinatione ſanctoram. De bono perſeverantiae,</hi> to name no more.</p>
               <p>The great difficulty now in this Conſequent of Election which appears, does undoubtedly lye here: <hi>If neither the faith nor good works of man do ſpring from his own free will, but from the grace of God and Election, then may the unbeliever and wicked excuſe themſelves, and ſay, It is not long of themſelves that they believe not, nor obey, but the cauſe is in God who gives them not faith and obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and they cannot help their own reprobation.</hi> They will not ſay that, Reprobation is any other than a <hi>negative</hi> decree, which infuſes no malice in them, but <hi>it denyes them that grace which Election gives others: and, if it be not in their power to beleeve and repent without that grace, How can they be condemned for their not beleeving and repenting?</hi> This difficulty I am aſſured did ſtick ſo faſt upon this Father in his <hi>firſt</hi> writings, that I do hardly think him quite out of the gravell in any of his <hi>laſt.</hi> Let us turn to his book <hi>De ſpiritu &amp; littera.</hi> In his one and thirtieth Chapter, he offers the queſtion, <hi>Whether faith be in mans power,</hi> and determines that it is, and muſt be ſo? Upon this in his thirty third chapter he comes to another queſtion which is put to the quick, <hi>Whether the will whereby he believes,</hi> be therefore of <hi>himſelf,</hi> or of <hi>God?</hi> If it be not of our ſelves (ſayes he) but of Gods gift, then may man ſay (according to the objection propoſed) that he beleeved not, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe God gave him not the will. If it be of our ſelves, How can that text of the Apoſtle, <hi>what haſt thou, O man, thou didſt not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive,</hi> be true; ſeeing this <hi>will</hi> to beleeve he hath of himſelf?
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:56460:5"/>For the extricating us out of this diſtreſſe, he yields to the firſt, and ſeems convinced, that faith muſt be both in our own <hi>power,</hi> and <hi>of our ſelves,</hi> for that reaſon. <hi>Dicit Apoſtolus, Idem Deus qui operatur omnia in omnibus: nuſquam autem dictum eſt, Deus credit omnia in omnibus. Quod ergo credimus, noſtrum eſt: quod autem bonum operamur, illius eſt qui credentibus dat Spiritum ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctum.</hi> In his Expoſition upon the Romans. <hi>The Apoſtle ſayes that God works all in all, but never that he beleeves all in all. That We beleeve therefore, it is of our ſelves: but that we do good works it is of him who gives his holy Spirit to them that beleeve.</hi> To the laſt therefore he chooſes to anſwer: <hi>Liberum arbitrium naturaliter attributum a Creatore animae rationali, illa media vis eſt, quae vel intendi ad fidem, vel inclinari ad infidelita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem poteſt. Et idco, nec iſtam voluntatem qua credit Deo, dici poteſt homo habere quam non acceperit, quandoquidem vocante Deo ſurgit de libero arbitrio quod naturaliter cum vocaretur accepit: Vult autem omnes homines ſalvos fore &amp; in agnitionem veritatis venire, non ſic tamen ut eis adimat liberum arbitrium, quo vel bene vel male utentes juſtiſſime judicentur.</hi> The ſubſtance is, that, <hi>The will whereby we beleeve may be ſaid to be received of God, although it proceed from our ſelves, becauſe the faculty from whence it ariſes, is received from him;</hi> that is, Becauſe the <hi>nature</hi> we have, is of our Creator, the <hi>will</hi> which is of <hi>nature,</hi> is of Him.</p>
               <p>This does not ſatisfy me, for theſe reaſons.
<list>
                     <item>1. That which the Father ſayes as to the <hi>voluntas qua credimus, The will whereby we beleeve,</hi> I take to be the ſame which <hi>Pelagius</hi> ſaid as to the <hi>volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas qua bene operamur, The will whereby we doe good works.</hi> But if this text, and ſuch as this, be good againſt <hi>Pelagius,</hi> they muſt be good againſt <hi>Auguſtine</hi> here, that neither is our <hi>faith</hi> of our ſelves, upon the ſame account. The truth is, The judgment of this Father while he wrot this book, is this. The Spirit is given to a man upon his beleeving. This Spirit infuſes grace, charity, or ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification. This charity is that which diſpoſes to good works. <hi>Good works</hi> therefore (he counts) muſt be of grace and Gods ſpirit, and to follow juſtification which is with him this infuſed grace: But as for <hi>beleeving</hi> which is the firſt thing upon which the Spirit it ſelf is given to infuſe this grace, from whence our good works doe ſpring; this muſt ariſe, he accounts, from mans free will, or
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:56460:5"/>elſe the fault will not be in himſelf (which is the argument convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces him), but it muſt lye on the will of God onely, that he hath not the ſpirit, and ſo no grace, and ſo does not well, and is not ſaved. Whether this argument be irrefragable or no, we ſhall ſee by what will follow.</item>
                     <item>2. There are two queſtions raiſed toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by the Apoſtle, <hi>Who maketh thee to differ from another?</hi> and, <hi>What haſt thou, O man, that thou didſt not receive?</hi> The chief dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty lyes in anſwering the former queſtion; for, by that is the <hi>ſecond</hi> to be regulated. Now if that we have from God is onely this <hi>middle faculty,</hi> which we may uſe to <hi>beleeve,</hi> or <hi>not,</hi> Who is it makes the difference in one mans uſing it to <hi>faith,</hi> and another's to <hi>infidelity!</hi> That which is the <hi>leſs,</hi> the <hi>Poſſe velle, The power to will</hi> ſhall be of God (that is, of Nature, and ſo of God): but the <hi>Ipſum velle, The will or willing it ſelf,</hi> which is the <hi>greater,</hi> and which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed ſaves us, ſhall be of our ſelves.</item>
                     <item>3. The Scripture is expreſs concerning faith. — <hi>and that not of our ſelves, it is the gift of God.</hi> If the word <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, there, referrs to the whole ſentence, we have o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther texts. <hi>No man cometh to me,</hi> that is, beleeveth in me <hi>unleſs the Father draw him. To you it is given not only to believe, but to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for his name. This is the work of God that you beleeve. Who hath firſt given to him? Of him and to him are all things. I obtained mercy That I ſhould be faithfull,</hi> not Becauſe I was faithfull. <hi>But ye beleeve not, becauſe ye are not of my ſheep.</hi> Again, <hi>As many as were ordained to ſalvation, beleeved.</hi> It ſeems here that the cauſe why ſome <hi>beleeve</hi> and ſome beleeve <hi>not,</hi> is their being, or not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the number of thoſe who are <hi>ordained</hi> to be of his <hi>flock.</hi> The like text in reference to <hi>works,</hi> as theſe to <hi>faith,</hi> is that to the Epheſians, <hi>He hath choſen us in him before the foundation of the world that we ſhould be holy.</hi> It is not therefore mans <hi>faith</hi> or <hi>holineſs</hi> is the cauſe of Gods <hi>Election,</hi> but it is Gods <hi>election</hi> is the cauſe of mans <hi>holineſs</hi> and <hi>faith.</hi> A prime and eternal cauſe (ſay our Divines) cannot depend upon the ſelf ſame temporal effects which are thereby cauſed. If therefore the Ordination of God be the cauſe from whence mans faith and <hi>holineſs</hi> are derived; his foreſeen-faith, or foreſeen-works are not to be imagined antece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent cauſes, merits, conditions, or motives unto the Divine Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtination.</item>
                     <item>4. We have St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> acknowledging himſelf to have bin herein in an errour: So that theſe arguments muſt be
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:56460:6"/>no longer againſt <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> but againſt thoſe who have taken up that opinion he forſook. <hi>In nullo gloriandum eſt, dixit Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prianus, quoniam, noſtrum nihil ſit. Quod ut oſtenderet adhibuit A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtolum, Quid autem habes, quod non accepiſti? Quo praecipue teſtimonio convict us ſum cum errarem, putans fidem qua in Deum exedimus, non eſſe donum Dei, ſed a nobis eſſe in nobis: &amp; per illam nos impetrare Dei dona, quibus temperanter, &amp; juſte, &amp; pie viva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus in hoc ſeculo. Quem errorem nonnulla opuſcula mea ſatis indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant. It was the ſaying of bleſſed Cyprian, that we may glory in no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, becauſe that which is ours is nothing. This he proved by the words of the Apoſtle. By which teſtimony I was firſt convinced when I erred, thinking that faith was of our ſelves, and then good works obtained by it. Which errour ſeveral of my former pieces do ſufficiently ſhew. De praedeſtinatione ſanctor.</hi> c. 3. I wiſh he had mentioned the book here which I am citing, as he does one or two other, that I might have known his ſolution to the difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty which himſelf hath urged, but left unanſwered upon our hands.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>To return then to the Father's queſtion, Whether the <hi>Voluntas qua credimus, The will whereby we beleeve,</hi> be of our ſelves, or God's gift? I muſt not chooſe the <hi>firſt</hi> with him in that book, but the <hi>laſt</hi> according to other of his works. Nevertheleſs, we muſt care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully diſtinguiſh the two things whereof he hath made two queſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ions, <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>trum fides in noſtra conſtituta ſit poteſtate, Whether faith be in our power,</hi> in one chapter: and, <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>trum voluntas qua credimus donum ſit Dei, an ex libertate arbitrii, Whether the will whereby we do beleeve, be the gift of God, or the effect of our own liberty,</hi> in another. I do apprehend here, that both theſe two things are to be held, That faith is in our power, and That the will whereby we beleeve is not of our ſelves, but of Gods grace or gift. The holding both theſe is that which cuts the thread of all difficulties in this matter. For the one, That faith is in <hi>mans power,</hi> we are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding verily to that Father. A thing is in a mans power, which he may do if he will. <hi>Hane dicimus poteſtatem, ubi voluntati ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iacet facultas faciendi.</hi> When he accounts Faith then to be in mans power, he underſtands this, That he may beleeve if he will. And this is a truth of great neceſſity, yet hath difficulty: But when he proceeds hereupon ſo farre, as to make the <hi>will</hi> therefore <hi>where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:56460:6"/>we beleeve</hi> to be <hi>of our ſelves,</hi> it was a ſtep which himſelf ſaw need, to draw back. There are many things that are <hi>poſſible,</hi> which yet never <hi>ſhall be,</hi> as this Father himſelf gives inſtances of, upon another occaſion, in the firſt chapter of this book. There are likewiſe many things which a man <hi>can</hi> do, that yet he never <hi>will,</hi> or is like to do without ſome ſpeciall cauſe moving him to it. Such is the buſineſs of mans Converſion. There is no man (we are to hold with him) but he may <hi>beleeve,</hi> I will adde, <hi>repent,</hi> and be <hi>ſaved,</hi> if he <hi>will:</hi> yet is this to be known and held alſo, That there is no man for certain ever <hi>will,</hi> unleſs it be from that one ſpecial cauſe which is Gods grace, or the Spirit's motion that works his heart thereunto. Now then, Shall a man remain an unbeleever, and impenitent and periſh, the fault ſhall lye upon himſelf, and God ſhall be juſt, becauſe we place faith in his own <hi>power.</hi> He may believe, and repent, and be ſaved, if he <hi>will.</hi> If God <hi>would</hi> and he <hi>will not,</hi> he may thank himſelf. Again, if he do believe, and repent, and is ſaved, he ſhall have no cauſe to boaſt or glory in himſelf, becauſe that though he might believe and repent if he would, yet <hi>would</hi> he never have repented while the world laſted, he would have bin damn'd firſt, if it had not bin for the grace of God that wrought him over, after he had ſtood ſo long out. And this is a ſad truth I grant, which needs not the proof of one or two ſingle texts, when the ſcope of the whole Scripture which at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributes our <hi>deſtructon</hi> to our <hi>ſelves,</hi> and our life and <hi>help</hi> unto <hi>God,</hi> does ſeal to it. <hi>Who is it hath made thee to differ? Of him we have the will and the deed. By grace, ye are ſaved.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>You may ſay, If the <hi>will</hi> then be of God, why does he not give the <hi>will,</hi> as well as the <hi>power</hi> to all, ſeeing he would have all men to be ſaved? I anſwer in the firſt place what <hi>Auguſtine</hi> hath be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, that God will have all men to be ſaved and come to the knowledge of the truth; but yet ſo as the free will of man be not deſtroyed. My meaning though, is not as I take the Father's to be there, as if the <hi>will in believeing</hi> could not be of God (of unwilling making man willing) but this freedome were loſt; when I doubt not but the caſe is the ſame in <hi>believeing</hi> as in <hi>well-doing,</hi> where mans free will, and Gods grace would ſtand together alwayes in his account. I ſay farther, God will have all to be ſaved in vouchſafing the <hi>means</hi> to all, to be <hi>ſaved if they will.</hi> This ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:56460:7"/>in theſe three particulars.
<list>
                     <item>1. That he hath given his Son to dye for all the world.</item>
                     <item>2. The Lord Jeſus hath by his death procured the New Covenant, or ſuch termes upon which Salvation may be had, as are <hi>poſſible</hi> to all the World. This is a point to be known, that there is this difference between the Covenant of <hi>Works,</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der which we are by Nature, and the Covenant of <hi>Grace,</hi> unto which we are Redeemed; that, The condition of the one, as to our falne Eſtate is <hi>Impoſſible,</hi> and the condition of the other is <hi>Poſſible.</hi> If it be not poſſible, or in Mans <hi>Power</hi> to perform if he will, then hath Chriſt done nothing for the World, but died onely for his Elect. For, To procure a Benefit on a Condition that is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible, is all one, as to procure no Benefit at all.</item>
                     <item>3. There is ſufficient light by the Goſpel, or by other means from <hi>within</hi> and <hi>without,</hi> to inſtruct all men, ſo that if they be not wanting to that Light, they may be ſaved: And thus are we to make good this Truth, God will have all to be ſaved, <hi>if they will of themſelves;</hi> which yet doth not hinder, but he may will the Salvation of ſome more than ſo, that is, not only if they Will of <hi>themſelves;</hi> but if they Will by his <hi>Grace,</hi> which he gives, or refuſes to whom he pleaſes.</item>
                  </list>
                  <hi>Cur autem illum adjuvet Deus, illum non adjuvet: Illum tantum, illum non tantum; iſtum illo, illum iſto modo, penes ipſum eſt, &amp; aequitatis tam ſecreta ratio, &amp; excellentia poteſtatis. But why He helps this man, and not that? this man ſo much, and that man not ſo much; this man one way, that man another; we muſt leave it to Him, whoſe Power and Wiſdom is above our reach. De peccatorum meritis &amp; remiſſione,</hi> l. 2. c. 5.</p>
               <p>I know indeed, The Scripture ſpeaks ordinarily of a <hi>Cannot;</hi> but there is a <hi>Cannot</hi> which denotes an <hi>Impoſſibility,</hi> and a <hi>Cannot</hi> which denotes an <hi>Indiſpoſition</hi> onely. In the Parables, the Steward ſays <hi>be cannot digg;</hi> and the Man in Bed, he <hi>cannot riſe.</hi> In the ſame ſenſe the Scripture ſays, <hi>We cannot come to Chriſt, unleſs we be Drawen:</hi> and we <hi>cannot learn to do well, that are accuſtomed to do evil.</hi> When a man is ſo diſpoſed againſt any thing, as that he certainly never will do it under that diſpoſition, it is common for us to ſay <hi>he cannot;</hi> as of the Idle perſon, we ſay, <hi>he cannot work;</hi> of the Abſtemious, <hi>he cannot drink.</hi> The Scripture accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modates it ſelf to our Language: <hi>He that is born of God, cannot ſin,</hi> ſayes the Apoſtle: That is, he is under that diſpoſition
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:56460:7"/>through the <hi>New Nature,</hi> that he can no more find in his heart to live in any deliberate courſe of ſin, than the Wicked can endure to come up to an Univerſal unreſerved Reſignation of himſelf un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God. Thus are we to underſtand ſuch Texts. St. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> I remember, in the book laſt quoted, which he perſues, <hi>De ſpiritu &amp; litera,</hi> is very wary of denying a <hi>Poſſibility</hi> to a man, even of living without ſin, when he is induſtriouſly proving that none in Earth but do ſin; and there are ſome learned Divines ſtand much on this, that we have our <hi>faculties,</hi> and the <hi>object</hi> ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>propoſed;</hi> and therefore a <hi>Natural Power</hi> to every thing which is our duty. But the Father is more cautious, who diſtinguiſhes between what we can do by <hi>Nature,</hi> and what by <hi>Grace: With<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out me,</hi> ſayes Chriſt, <hi>ye can do nothing;</hi> and <hi>through Him,</hi> ſayes the Apoſtle, <hi>I am able to do all things.</hi> By <hi>Grace</hi> he thinks it ſafeſt to hold that <hi>Poſſible,</hi> which by <hi>Nature,</hi> or to our bare na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural ſtrength and faculties, he doubts-not to count <hi>Impoſſible.</hi> There is a <hi>medium</hi> therefore between both. They that dare ſay, If it be the duty of a man that is without Grace, to live perfectly, it is poſſible; or, That it is in the power of man, in the ſtate of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, without Grace, to keep all Gods Commandements, and live without ſin, becauſe it is his <hi>Duty,</hi> are too boyſterous on the one hand; for, <hi>Auguſtine</hi> does manifeſtly account this to be the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treameſt Pelagianiſm; and the Father, I count, in framing this di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction for this purpoſe, is too tender on the other. It is true, a man hath his Natural Faculties, and the Object may be revealed, but theſe faculties are corrupt and unſutable to the object. There is <hi>Nature</hi> then, and <hi>corrupt Nature.</hi> The Scripture ſpeaks of Man as he <hi>is;</hi> and that is impoſſible to <hi>Falne Nature,</hi> which to <hi>Original Nature</hi> was poſſible. The Law it ſelf nevertheleſs, being founded in Gods Nature, and Man as Created after his Image; is unchangable, and cannot ceaſe to require of all men, what it did at firſt of <hi>Adam,</hi> when given in Innocency. It is the duty conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently of every body, whether he hath Grace, or hath not, To keep this perfect Law of our Maker entire; but we are not to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm it to be <hi>Poſſible,</hi> or within the power of any whatſoever. No certainly, ſeeing the Scripture tells us ſo often, and ſo flatly, that, <hi>By the deeds of the Law, no fleſh living ſhall be juſtified:</hi> See<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing there is no man but is born in original ſin, which he cannot
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:56460:8"/>help; and the Apoſtle calls Concupiſcence, ſin; and ſeeing the Grace of God, or the Spirit, is not given to any for their fulfilling the <hi>Law ef Works,</hi> but the <hi>Law of Grace</hi> (which is a point not conſidered on by <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> I take it, and moſt others), we muſt chooſe rather to ſay that the whole duty indeed of man, according to the Law of Works, (take it together) is <hi>Impoſſible;</hi> for, ſo does the Apoſtle, I account, intend in that expreſſion, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. That is as much as to ſay, <hi>The Law in that, through the weakneſs of the fleſh, none is able to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form it, cannot poſſibly juſtifie any.</hi> The impoſſibility lying on <hi>us</hi> in regard to the performance, not in <hi>it.</hi> True, it were poſſible through ſuch an extraordinary meaſure of the Spirit as the Man-Chriſt had (not to leave <hi>Auguſtine</hi> quite), but that meaſure be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing not to be given to any body elſe, it is beſt ſaid, to be <hi>Impoſſible,</hi> even by the ſtrength of <hi>Nature,</hi> &amp; by <hi>Grace</hi> (according to its ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary meaſure on Earth) <hi>Impoſſible;</hi> when yet, as for the terms of the <hi>Law of Faith,</hi> I hold it fit ſtill, to ſay, they are <hi>Poſſible</hi> to all; though there is none <hi>do</hi> perform them, but by <hi>Grace.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Upon this, there is one thing needs muſt yet be ſpoken to, for it hath ſtuck ſome time upon my ſelf. It is this; when <hi>Auguſtine</hi> is telling us that Faith is in our power, he offers us this Reaſon, Becauſe a man may believe, or not believe, he accounts what he will. <hi>Hoc quiſque in poteſtate habere dicitur, quod, ſi vult, facit; ſi non vult, non facit. Vide nunc utrum quiſquam credat ſi noluerit, aut non credat ſi voluerit. That every man is ſaid to have in his power, which, if he will, he does; and, if he will not, he does not. Conſider now, whether there be any that believe if they will not, or do not believe if they will.</hi> The contrary to this I judg is certain, that there are ſome things I <hi>cannot</hi> believe though I <hi>would,</hi> and ſome things that I cannot but believe, though I would <hi>not</hi> never ſo fain. From whence I ſhould oppoſe therefore that <hi>Faith</hi> then, whatſoever elſe is, cannot be in mans <hi>Power,</hi> no more than it is of his own <hi>Will.</hi> For ſatisfaction to which, I acknowledg that there are Doctrines or Propoſitions which are true, that many a man cannot believe if he will; nay perhaps ſome Articles that the Ancients have impoſed as neceſſary to Salvation. I ſay, I acknowledg that a man cannot make himſelf to believe what he will, nor otherwiſe than he does believe; nevertheleſs, I do apprehend that that-Faith,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:56460:8"/>which is the condition of the covenant of grace is indeed in mans power. I apprehend that whereas the conditions of the Covenant of grace are, and muſt be, ſuch as are poſſible, there is no man who believes as much as he <hi>can;</hi> but his <hi>will</hi> ſhall be accepted for whatſoever is required more, which he <hi>cannot,</hi> and which is not <hi>given.</hi> Or elſe we had a good have bin left ſtill to the covenant of works. The condition then of the Covenant of grace, or thoſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>erms which remain of neceſſity of ſalvation, does not lye in an aſſent to every doctrine and article which is true in the Chriſtian religion, but to ſo much as ſerves to bring a man unto Chriſt, or unto God, <hi>Without faith it is impoſſible to pleaſe God, for he that comes unto him muſt beleeve that he is, and that he is a rewarder of them that diligently ſeek him.</hi> And ſuch a faith as this, will the light of Nature inſtruct every man to. Though where the Goſpel is preached, the beliefe of Chriſt alſo, in his perſon, offices, word, and works, will and muſt neceſſarily follow, ſeeing, <hi>To whom much is given, of him ſhall much be required. Ye beleeve in God, beleeve alſo in mee. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nleſs ye beleeve I am he, ye ſhall dye in your ſins.</hi> Now, let us bring that faith a man has to the teſt. If my beleeving of God, or Chriſt, that he will be good to me if I repent, does produce this repentance, then is my faith ſaving and ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectual: if it do not, then is the fault in my <hi>will.</hi> When it lyes on my will then, it is in my <hi>power:</hi> yet if I will I muſt hold it to be ſtill of the grace of God. <hi>Huc valere debet tota Dei notitia</hi> (ſayes <hi>Calvin</hi>), <hi>ut omne bonum ab illo petere, &amp; illi acceptum ferre diſcamus. To this purpoſe does the whole knowledge of God which is taught us in Scripture conduce, that we ſhould learne to ſeek all our good at his hands, and live in the return of our thank-fulneſs to him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When God <hi>made</hi> man, he muſt know the end of his <hi>work</hi> He muſt foreſee what man will do, what his poſterity will do, all that they will do, the end of all. When God foreſees the actions of man, it muſt be conceived in the order of nature that they will <hi>be,</hi> before he foreſees them: and, if they will be, they muſt have ſome <hi>cauſe,</hi> and that cauſe muſt depend on the firſt Cauſe, and ſo all be reſolved into God's will. It is true, that he foreſees alſo what is <hi>poſſible</hi> as well as <hi>future:</hi> but a thing is poſſible only, becauſe he will it not; &amp; future becauſe he wills it. I ſay not, that this inferrs a <hi>Phyſical de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terminate influx</hi> into every act of man, which, proceeding from his
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:56460:9"/>free will is ſometimes good and ſometimes evill: it is ſufficient that there is ſuch a complexion of circumſtances provided, as that a <hi>vaga moralis infallibilitas, a morall indetermined certainty</hi> as to the event, ſhall ariſe out of the whole together, according to his eternal coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel. As for ſin or evill; it is a defect of Entity or good, a <hi>priva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive</hi> no <hi>poſitive</hi> thing, and ſo is of our <hi>ſelves,</hi> and not of <hi>Him,</hi> as <hi>Auguſtine</hi> againſt the <hi>Manichees, and the Schools</hi> after him have it. What followes now upon this, but that there is not an <hi>act</hi> of a mans whole <hi>life,</hi> or <hi>will,</hi> ſo farre as either <hi>ſub genere Entis,</hi> or <hi>ſub ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nere Morum</hi> it is <hi>good,</hi> but it muſt be of God.</p>
               <p>And what then is there to mate that Father's doctrine of Electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as it is laid on this fonndation? Let us give the mind its greateſt liberty. One may think. As there are ſome things which are <hi>not poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible,</hi> &amp; it is no derogation to Gods <hi>power</hi> to ſay he <hi>cannot do</hi> them: ſo may there be ſome things <hi>non ſcibilia, not knowable,</hi> &amp; it ſhall not derogate from his <hi>Omniſciency</hi> to ſay he <hi>foreknows not</hi> them. Such things as are left altogether to the will of a free agent, may be thought ſuch. There are ſome things depend on mans will, which God <hi>determines;</hi> and here hee foreknows mens wills, becauſe he <hi>knowes</hi> as well as <hi>does,</hi> whatſoever he <hi>will:</hi> and there are ſome things depend on mans will which we are to conceive that he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termines <hi>not,</hi> but will have <hi>contingent;</hi> and here to make God ſuch a one as that he muſt foreſee every thing whether he will or no, and that a <hi>contingent</hi> to him ſhall be impoſſible though he would have a <hi>contingent,</hi> does ſeem to be an affront to his Majeſtie, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than a perfection. To this purpoſe we read that when God ſaw that <hi>the thoughts of mans heart were evill continually,</hi> it is ſaid <hi>it repented him that he made man.</hi> And we have many expreſſions of the like import. O that my people had bin thus and thus, or would be thus and thus! <hi>Thou art a gracious God, and mercifull, ſlow to anger, and of great kindneſs, and repenteſt thee of the evill.</hi> And why may we not frame our notion of God from ſuch texts of Scripture as theſe, as well as from others, and rather than from the definition of the Schools? Eſpecially if we can make God more lovely to our ſelves &amp; more adorable, than by their concep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. There is nothing that God does will <hi>now,</hi> but what he did decree <hi>always.</hi> And why ſo? Becauſe, the Schools ſay, there will elſe be <hi>compoſition</hi> in God, the compoſition of an <hi>eſſence</hi> and <hi>acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent,</hi>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:56460:9"/>and God is a <hi>pure act, &amp; ens ſimpliciſſimum.</hi> But what if the Conceptions of thoſe holy men, who would have God like to man in regard of the Scripture <hi>expreſſions</hi> (wherein they were ſo zealous, as we have a famous Eccleſiaſtical ſtory about it), ſhould not be ſo injurious on one hand to the Almighty, as ſuch Concepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons as theſe on the other, which do quite puzzle our Intellectuals, and leave us without any quick ſenſe at all of him? It is certain that God is <hi>Good, Righteous, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nchangeable:</hi> but we muſt have a Concep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of goodneſs, righteouſneſs and unchangeableneſs, and that which is <hi>agreeable</hi> to that herein, which we eſteem <hi>perfections</hi> in our ſelves, before we attribute them to him. When we make God then to be always gracious to thoſe that do well, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſed with evil, and ſo brings, or determines to bring a <hi>Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> on one, and beſtows a <hi>Bleſſing</hi> on another, according as he ſees at the preſent the <hi>Provocation</hi> of the one, and <hi>Obedience</hi> of the other, without any other <hi>determination before,</hi> beſides that of his <hi>Law;</hi> why is not this an <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nchangeableneſs,</hi> more worthy the <hi>Divine Excellence,</hi> than that, by which he being conceived a <hi>pure act,</hi> muſt be made never to will any thing elſe, than what he wills at once from all Eternity?</p>
               <p>Upon the like Hypotheſis as this, one may alſo propoſe a ſuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble notion of Praedeſtination. To wit, that the Scripture being skanned to the bottom, Election perhaps may be found indeed no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe but Gods determination to ſave Men and Women by the Covenant of Grace, and not by the Covenant of our Greati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or by the <hi>Righteouſneſs of God</hi> declared in the Goſpel, and not by the <hi>Righteouſneſs of Works.</hi> This definition ſhould be founded on ſuch Texts, where the <hi>purpoſe of God, according to E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection,</hi> is ſaid to be <hi>not of Works, but of him that calleth.</hi> And <hi>He hath called us not according to our works, but according to his purpoſe and Grace.</hi> It ſhould be founded alſo on the inſtances of <hi>Iſaack</hi> and <hi>Jacob,</hi> in whom <hi>the Children of the Promiſe</hi> are Elected, in oppoſition to <hi>the Children of the fleſh;</hi> that is, thoſe that look for Juſtification by the deeds of the Law. And thus have we the example of the Jews rejection upon that account. And thus when a Phariſee hath lived ſo Righteouſly, that as to the whole <hi>Law</hi> he is <hi>blameleſs,</hi> and ſo truſts to <hi>his Righteouſneſs,</hi> ſhall ſay, And why am I rejected for all this, and ſuch a Publican onely for his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penting and truſting on the mercy of God, through Chriſt is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted?
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:56460:10"/>it may be anſwered, the reaſon is plain, becauſe it is <hi>God</hi> that <hi>makes the difference,</hi> by decreeing and appointing what <hi>terms</hi> he pleaſes, upon which one ſhall be ſaved, and not another. <hi>Hath not the Potter power over his Clay,</hi> of what <hi>ſort</hi> he will, to make Veſſels of <hi>honour</hi> and <hi>diſhonour?</hi> ſo that it is not <hi>of him that Will<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, or Runneth;</hi> it is not upon ſuch terms as a man himſelf ſets, or would ſet, of <hi>works;</hi> but it is of <hi>Grace,</hi> of <hi>him that ſheweth mercy.</hi> Well! But what would be the <hi>Conſequent</hi> of ſuch Doctrine as this? Why the <hi>Conſequent,</hi> no doubt, muſt be the ſame in effect with the Pelagian, which is <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Grace,</hi> and <hi>Free will</hi> to purpoſe. But I confeſs my ſelf to have imbibed the Doctrine of St <hi>Auguſtine</hi> from my younger years, that I am convinced by it, believing that nothing can be ſet up againſt it with any ſtrength, which is ſhort of <hi>Vorſtius;</hi> while <hi>Pelagius</hi> and <hi>Vorſtius</hi> both, are names we know that do ſo <hi>male audire, Are of ſuch ill report</hi> in the Church, as the <hi>Arminians</hi> themſelves will not bear. For our apprehenſions then of God, according to the Schools, it muſt be acknowledged, that he is ſaid in holy Scripture, to <hi>dwell in the Clouds and thick darkneſs;</hi> and into ſuch darkneſs, or thoſe Clouds, will I account indeed that he is put, while he is made to be <hi>actus purus,</hi> and wrapt in their notions, which if they ſerved no other, they do yet ſerve this end; even moſt reverendly and exceedingly to hide him from us, and render him thereby, but as he is, very truly incomprehenſible to us.</p>
               <p>To reflect then back on the difficulty before, as to the <hi>Conſequent</hi> of Election our way, if any ſay they are not ſatisfied with what I have ſaid, becauſe a power ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver produced into act, is as good as none. I anſwer, if I propoſe <hi>that</hi> which they <hi>would</hi> have, and it be all <hi>can</hi> be had, there is a <hi>meaſure</hi> in things, which when we have ſet in any point ſo, as the Determination cannot be paſſed, but we ſhall run into the extreams on one ſide, or the other, which we ſeek to avoid, we ought to be ſatisfied. Eſpecially when ſuch a power alone as this, which in the <hi>effect,</hi> without Grace, is <hi>none,</hi> will do our work. If we allow not a power to man, how ſhall God be juſt, how ſhall God condemn any (which is that lyes at bottome ſtill of of what is ſaid) for not doing that which was not in his <hi>power,</hi> or which was not <hi>poſſible?</hi> If when a man hath <hi>Power,</hi> he does alſo exert that power, and <hi>wills</hi> of himſelf; how ſhall ſuch Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:56460:10"/>be true which have been urged? <hi>It is God that makes us to differ. Of him we have the Will and the Deed:</hi> Nay, ſuch Texts more eſpecially, as ſpeak expreſly of a <hi>Cannot,</hi> when the true in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent and meaning of them is this, that we <hi>do not,</hi> and never <hi>will</hi> (as I have had it before) till God prevents us by his effectual Grace. Without Chriſt we can do nothing. All our ſufficiency is of God: No man can come to him unleſs he be drawen. <hi>Si non eſt liberum arbitrium quomodo Deus judicabit mundum? Si eſt liberum arbitrium, quomodo ſalvabit mundum? If man have not Free-will, how ſhall God judg him? If he have, how ſhall he ſave him?</hi> This is the difficulty of the Father. If then there be ſuch a <hi>liberum arbitrium</hi> to be found out, which <hi>quodam modo</hi> is <hi>ſine libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro arbitrio,</hi> ſuch a <hi>power,</hi> as in the effect is no <hi>power;</hi> that is, ſuch as without Grace (which alſo is efficacious) comes to no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, then can we decide this buſineſs for him. Suppoſe a Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate for ſome fault ſhall cut off a Malefactors hands, and then command him to write, and promiſe him great things if he will, and threaten him if he do not write, can we think this Magiſtrate ſerious? Is this becoming a righteous and good man? If you grant not man to have power, why do you <hi>Preach?</hi> why do you <hi>Exhort?</hi> If you will give him more than this (I muſt perſiſt), why do you <hi>Pray?</hi> why do you ask Grace of God? what is it to ask his Grace, but that God would incline the will? <hi>Alunt quor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum vocare hominem ad praeſtandam conditionem quam implere neque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at? It is objected, why are men called to that condition they cannot perform? Reſpondeo, poſſe, &amp; non poſſe eam implere. Non poſſunt niſi datur poſſe poſſunt tamen quia quod non poſſunt, pravitati eorum debetur.</hi> I <hi>anſwer</hi> (ſayes <hi>Conyer</hi>), <hi>They cannot, if it were not</hi> given (that which is onely of Nature is given), <hi>but they can, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is to be attributed to their wickedneſs alone, that they</hi> cannot. <hi>They can, and they cannot,</hi> Thus others ſay: <hi>They can, and they wont</hi> I ſay. Onely in regard this <hi>wont</hi> is never changed in any, but by ſpecial Grace; the Scripture (I have ſaid) calls it a <hi>can't.</hi> That is, it is a <hi>can</hi> in it ſelf, but a <hi>can't</hi> in the effect; it being in effect all one when you <hi>never will,</hi> as if you <hi>could</hi> not. What? when the Scripture ſayes, they can't, do I then ſay, they can? yes, becauſe my <hi>can, and never will</hi> (I affirm) is the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures <hi>can't. But there are ſome of you believe not. Therefore I
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:56460:11"/>ſaid unto you, that no man can come unto me, except it be given him. Some of you,</hi> notwithſtanding all my Preaching and Miracles, <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve not;</hi> therefore I ſaid unto you, you <hi>can't.</hi> And this inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation (I muſt adde) accords with the Ancients. <hi>Non potue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt, hoc eſt noluerunt. It a nonnunquam poteſtate pro voluntate utitur.</hi> Chryſoſtome <hi>on</hi> Jo. 12.39. So Auguſtine. <hi>Non pote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant quia nolebant, quippe eorum voluntatem praevidit Deus.</hi> Hoc <hi>autem quod dicit, non potuerunt credere, ſignificat, noluerunt. Nam malus &amp; improbus homo non poteſt credere quam diu talis fuerit, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la ſcilicet eligent &amp; volens</hi> Thophylact. <hi>Mundus odiſſe vos non po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt, &amp; Quomodo poteſtis bona loqui cum ſitis mali? Quo pacto quidquam horum impoſſibile eſt, niſi quod voluntas repugnat?</hi> Nazi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enzen. <hi>Impoſſibile dicitur quod, rariſſime contingit,</hi> according to one, <hi>quod difficilime per ficitur</hi> according to another. See <hi>Ruiz</hi> on that head, <hi>Impoſſibilitatem bene operandi Patres abhorrent, eti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am quamdiu illam ſonat expreſſe cortex Scripturae. Ad queſt</hi> 23, <hi>&amp;</hi> 24. <hi>Ex parte prima S. Thomae. Diſp.</hi> 39. <hi>Sec.</hi> 8.</p>
               <p>And here I cannot but <hi>inſert</hi> the <hi>mention</hi> of a late <hi>Diſcourſe</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout <hi>Natural</hi> and <hi>Moral Impotency,</hi> or <hi>Natural</hi> and <hi>Ethical po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer,</hi> which terms do expreſs this <hi>can</hi> and <hi>cannot</hi> with ſo much dex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terity, though my ſelf uſe them not, becauſe my Papers were on the Anvil before that book came out. And there is ſomthing therefore, I find, I have already, and after, puts me in mind <hi>of two things</hi> I want in that ſingular pretty Tract. One is, a little more tenderneſs in that inculcated aſſertion. <hi>The more moral Impotency, the more inexcuſable.</hi> I believe the Author was himſelf of a healthfull mind, and not ſenſible of thoſe imbred inclinations, and ſicklineſs which ſome ſoul are born with, &amp; no ſtrivings againſt it will utterly ſubdue, till death. There are beſides certain impreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions and wounds ſometimes on the <hi>imagination</hi> that are incurable. I do not doubt now, but God, who is moſt wiſe and good, <hi>who knoweth our frame</hi> (as the Pſalmiſt ſpeaks), <hi>and remembreth we are but Duſt,</hi> will conſider the ſeveral Conditions, Complexions, and Temptations that every man is obnoxious to in this life; and that there will be <hi>grains of allowance</hi> for <hi>ſome moral Impotency</hi> at the laſt day. <hi>Non ſine magna noſtra utilitate relinquitur nobis materia cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taminum ut humilietur ſanctitas dum pulſatur inſirmitas. It is not without our great benefit, that God does leave in his Children, mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:56460:11"/>for their ſpiritual Combat, that they may be humbled in their Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety, while they are aſſaulted with their infirmity.</hi> Ambroſe. <hi>De vocatione gentium.</hi> The other thing I want, is, a diſtinction in regard to that principle of his, and indeed foundation, which he inſiſts ſo much upon throughout the book. <hi>That which is our du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty muſt be poſſible.</hi> It is certain that <hi>perfection</hi> is ſtill our duty; and it is enough for us onely to make whatſoever is neceſſary to our Salvation to be in our power. Diſtinguiſh we muſt there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore between the <hi>Law of Works,</hi> and the <hi>Covenant of Grace.</hi> We are indeed to maintain the condition of the <hi>one</hi> to be <hi>poſſible</hi> for good reaſon; but as for what is required in the <hi>other,</hi> though it be ſtill our duty, and muſt remain ſo eternally (for Good and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil according to Nature, can never be changed), we are not to deny in our falne ſtate, to be <hi>impoſſible.</hi> Which hath been before Noted.</p>
               <p>To return, There is a point near a kinn to the matter in hand, of great difficulty, what part the <hi>will</hi> of man does bear in our good acts. That the beginning of all that is good, comes from God, who by his <hi>preventing</hi> Graee, works in us at firſt (as the Schools ſpeak) <hi>without us;</hi> and, That when the will is excited, he does work alſo <hi>with us,</hi> by his <hi>operating,</hi> or <hi>co-operating</hi> Grace, as the principal cauſe ſtill, and conſequently, That the whole good which is done, upon that account, is to be attributed to him, we ſhall find yeilded by the <hi>School men,</hi> as well as tendred by St. <hi>Auguſtine, Proſper, Fulgentius,</hi> and the like Fathers. <hi>Totum bonum eſt Deo tribuendum, quia totum Dens operatur.</hi> See <hi>Ruiz. De Deo operante; &amp; libero arbitrio,</hi> Sec. 1. On the other hand, That being <hi>acted,</hi> we <hi>act,</hi> and ſo concur with Gods Grace; That it is <hi>we</hi> Believe, Repent, and not God: <hi>We</hi> that work out our Salvation, though he gives the will and the deed: <hi>We</hi> who walk in his Statutes, though he puts his fear in our hearts to do it: and ſo <hi>We</hi> accordingly, who are bid to <hi>make our ſelves new hearts,</hi> which is his work out of queſtion; this is alſo undeniable in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. <hi>Deus eſt qui operatur—cum procul dubio, ſi homo ratione utatur, non poſſit credere, ſperare, diligere, niſi velit: nec pervenire ad palmam, niſi voluntate cucurrerit. It is God works in us, when beyond doubt, there is no man uſes his Reaſon, but it is himſelf alſo that wills.</hi> Aug. Enchir. c. 32. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t velimus, &amp; ſuum eſſe voluit &amp; noſtrum, ſuum vocando, noſtrum ſequendo,</hi> in another book. It
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:56460:12"/>is God then according to the determination of the ſchools, that is the <hi>principal</hi> cauſe, and the will of man the <hi>leſs principal,</hi> parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, <hi>ſecundary</hi> cauſe, of our good actions. His part indeed is ſuch to which all the glory is due, and yet ours ſuch as the good works are reckoned ours, and we ſhall be rewarded for them at the laſt day. When <hi>Calvin</hi> therefore ſeems here to oppoſe, I find him thus treated. <hi>Supponebat haereticus hominis arbitrium itae divina praedeſtinatione regi, ut quamvis operetur ſpontanee, nihil tamen agat ciun poteſtate non agendi, ſed agatur Dei operatione, That heritick</hi> Calvin (ſaies the now named learned Jeſuit out of Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleton) <hi>ſuppoſed the free will of man to be ſo governed by praedeſtina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that though it does act ſpontaneouſty, yet it acts not with a power of not acting, but it is acted by the operation of God.</hi> Well! what is the difference between them? Does <hi>Calvin</hi> indeed go to evacuate that <hi>free-will</hi> man hath by nature? no ſuch matter. Does he make the <hi>will</hi> to act ſo by Gods operation, as to have no operation of its own? I think not ſo. But I will tell you where the water ſticks. It ſticks between the <hi>Schools</hi> and <hi>Calvin,</hi> where it does between the <hi>Arminians</hi> and <hi>Calviniſts,</hi> and that is upon the point altogether of <hi>reſiſtibility</hi> or <hi>irreſiſtibility.</hi> The work of grace is underſtood by <hi>Calvin</hi> and the <hi>Calviniſts</hi> to be ſuch, as leaves not any <hi>power</hi> in the <hi>will</hi> to reſiſt, or of not acting. They doe ſtand ſo much on the bare term of Gods <hi>drawing</hi> us, as it leads them to ſpeak with exceſs. The truth therefore is to be thus decided. We are to hold with the Schools and <hi>Arminians,</hi> that the <hi>will</hi> hath ſtill power to reſiſt, or not to act, for mans nature is deſtroyed elſe: but we are to hold with the <hi>Calviniſt,</hi> that though it hath power, it never will, or does reſiſt, but will moſt certainly <hi>act,</hi> when it is <hi>acted</hi> by Gods electing grace. As in the caſe before of the <hi>Reprobate</hi> (I have ſaid), a man hath <hi>Power</hi> to beleeve, and repent, ſo that it is his fault, and he is juſtly condemned, if he do not, when yet he never <hi>will,</hi> for want of this grace: So in the caſe of the <hi>Elect,</hi> a man hath power to reſiſt, and not to act, but he will beleeve and repent infallibly, and never reſiſt, when he is wrought upon by it. The reaſon is, becauſe God by his <hi>prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtination</hi> of ſuch a perſon to life, does prepare a <hi>Vocation</hi> ſo <hi>Fit,</hi> and ſuited to his temper, condition, and the circumſtances he is in, as it ſhall inevitably carry the <hi>will</hi> (which by the way does recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cile
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:56460:12"/>the <hi>Certainty</hi> of the one, with the <hi>Liberty</hi> of the other, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to St. <hi>Auguſtine's</hi> intention), when the ſame means ſhall be uſed to a perſon not elect, but being not ſuited to his ſtate, they have no ſuch event: Even as the ſame phyſick given to two bodys diverſly diſpoſed, hath an operation upon one, and does the other no good. In ſhort, the grace of God is <hi>reſiſtible</hi> with the <hi>Armini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> in regard of <hi>power:</hi> it is <hi>irreſiſtible</hi> with the <hi>Calviniſts,</hi> in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of the <hi>effect.</hi> The <hi>will</hi> does ever retain its <hi>Phyſical power</hi> to act, or not act; when yet it is made <hi>Ethically impotent</hi> (to uſe once the Authour before) to reſiſt. <hi>Quisquis andet dicere, habeo ex me ipſo fidem, non ergo accepi, profecto contradicit apertiſſimae veritati: non quia credere vel non credere non eſt in arbitrio voluntatis, ſed in electis praeparatur voluntas a domino. If any dare ſay I have faith of my ſelf, and therefore did not receive it, he does for certain contradict the truth. Not becauſe that to believe or not beleeve is not in the power of the will, but in the Elect the will is prepared of God. Aug. De</hi> Praedeſ. Sanc. <hi>c.</hi> 5. We may add St. <hi>Ambroſs</hi> (or <hi>Proſper</hi> rather). <hi>Qui ad obediendum ſibi ipſum velle ſic donat, ut etiam a perſevera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turis illam mutabilitatem, quae poteſt nolle, non auferat.</hi> In one of his two books, <hi>De vocatione gentium.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſumm is, where a man beleeves, repents, and is converted, the <hi>difference</hi> is <hi>made</hi> between him and the reprobate. This is <hi>act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall,</hi> or <hi>created</hi> praedeſtination. Man concurrs in this work: nevertheleſs, in regard that it is not through his own ſtrength, or through that grace which is univerſal, or <hi>common</hi> to the <hi>Reprobate</hi> with the <hi>Elect,</hi> but through that grace which is peculiar and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared by <hi>increated</hi> predeſtination for him, it is not of himſelf, but of God, that he is <hi>made to differ.</hi> And if it be granted, that it is in his power to hinder the difference, while grace is making of it, ſeeing it is in his power ſtill not to act: but yet be aſſerted alſo, that the decree working infallibly, carrys the <hi>will,</hi> that it never is, or ſhall be hindered when that works: I do not ſee but this controverſie about <hi>Gods operation,</hi> and <hi>mans free will,</hi> may be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed. <hi>How is it ſaid</hi> (ſayes <hi>Auguſtine</hi>), <hi>it is not of him that willeth or runneth, but of God that ſheweth mercy? If it were to be underſtood onely becauſe it is of both, then might we ſay it is not of God likewiſe that ſheweth mercy, but of him that willeth and runs. But when no Chriſtian dare ſay ſo, it remains</hi> (ſayes he) <hi>to be ſo
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:56460:13"/>underſtood, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t totum Deo detar, qui homini voluntatem bonam &amp; praeparat adjuvandam, &amp; adjuvat praeparatam; That the whole be given to God, who both fits the will for his help, &amp; then helps it, being made fit. Enchiridion ad Laurentium,</hi> c. 32.</p>
               <p>As for the <hi>way</hi> of the Papiſts, that is, which the Trent Councel does tread, it ſeems to me verily an <hi>invented, forced</hi> way. They would avoid the cenſure of <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> and former Councels which condemned <hi>Pelagius,</hi> yet in effect do entend but the ſame thing. They ſay, therefore, that God does vouchſafe his grace to all; with this grace ſome <hi>co operate,</hi> and ſome do not. Thoſe that will co-operate with it God fore-ſees, and praedeſtinates them: thoſe that co-operate not, he rejects and condemns. By this means they will avoid making their own works to be the cauſe of their Election, ſeeing they can attribute all to this ſufficient aſſiſtance; when yet the <hi>conſequent</hi> of their opinion comes to one, that it muſt lye in the <hi>will of</hi> man which <hi>co operates,</hi> or <hi>co-operates</hi> not with this aſſiſtance, to <hi>make the difference,</hi> why <hi>one</hi> is choſen and ſaved, and not the <hi>other.</hi> That which is ſaid by the <hi>Pelagian,</hi> placing Grace only in <hi>Doctrine,</hi> or the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> is more ſingle I take it than this. It is true, there are ſome others beſides the Papiſts, are willing to hold Election to be of <hi>Works,</hi> or of <hi>Faith foreſeen,</hi> who will yet deny the <hi>Conſequent,</hi> that our Faith, and and good Works therefore muſt ariſe from our own free wills, and be meritorious; becauſe they will ſuppoſe them ſo foreſeen, (which the Papiſt I ſuppoſe ſay too) as to be wrought in us, or performed by Gods grace. But let me ask then, what they mean by this <hi>Grace?</hi> If they mean ſuch as in <hi>effectual,</hi> and determins the will, and ſo is <hi>peculiar</hi> to the Elect, Lo here the Doctrine of abſolute Election: If, they mean ſuch only as leaves the <hi>will</hi> in <hi>aequilibrio,</hi> to be determined ſtill of it ſelf, then the matter returns to the former iſſue. I will therefore cloſe up this point of Electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with the obſervation of that very judicious perſon that wrote the Councel of <hi>Trent.</hi> who having ſet down the debate of the Doctors about it, and divided them into two opinions, which comes in effect (without reciting the whole) to the tenents of <hi>ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute</hi> and <hi>conditional</hi> Election, he gives us his judgment. <hi>The firſt Opinion</hi> (ſayes he) <hi>which is</hi> Auguſtines, <hi>as it is myſtical and hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, keeping the mind humble, and relying on God without any con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:56460:13"/>in it ſelf; knowing the deformity of Sin, and excellency of Divine Grace: So was the ſecond plauſible, and popular, cheriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Humane Preſumption, and making a great ſhew; and it pleaſed more the Preaching Fryers, than the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding Divines. The Defenders of this, uſing Humane reaſons, prevailed againſt the others: But coming to the Teſtimonies of Scripture, they were manifeſtly e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vercom.</hi> I deſcend not to the more minute Diſputations, <hi>De praedeterminatione phyſica,</hi> between the <hi>Dominicans,</hi> and <hi>Franciſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cans;</hi> or <hi>De ſcentia media,</hi> among the <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> which are of lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer date (I count) in the World, and ought not to make us trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. I leave alſo the <hi>Janſeniſt</hi> and <hi>Moliniſt</hi> to that Bone; <hi>Haec praedeſtinatio Sanctorum nihil aliud eſt quam praeſcientia ſcilicet, &amp; praeparatio beneficiorum Dei, quibus certiſſime liberantur quicunque liberantur. This Predeſtination of the Saints, is nothing elſe but the Fore-knowledge, and Preparation of thoſe Benefits of God, whereby they are moſt certainly ſaved, that are ſaved.</hi> Aug. De bono, perſ. <hi>c.</hi> 14.</p>
               <p>There are two Opinions yet I ſhall mention, which are ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular; I do not think them true, yet am I pleaſed with any in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent for compoſing the Scripture. The one is that, aſcribed to <hi>Catarinus</hi> at <hi>Trent,</hi> to <hi>Occam,</hi> and others; That there are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed ſome few Perſons, who are Elected <hi>Abſolutely;</hi> of theſe God takes a ſpecial care that they never fail; as we read of <hi>Peter:</hi> But that the reſt of Mankind are left to univerſal Grace, and the liberty of their wills, under a <hi>Conditional</hi> Election, and Reprobation. The other is an Opinion of a Learned Doctor of another Profeſſion, very Studious of the Holy Writings; who is often telling me when I ſee him, That, <hi>Election is only to a Church-State, and peculiar Priviledges:</hi> But that we read of a <hi>Common Salvation.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:56460:14"/>
               <head>Of Redemption.</head>
               <p>I Do not remember any thing in St. <hi>Auguſtin</hi> that is peculiar about this Doctrine: Only I take notice from ſeveral paſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, that he goes ſtill the Narrow Way: That the Elect only are redeemed: That none but thoſe who are brought into the Church, by receiving all her Articles, and being Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized, can be of that Number. That no Heathen, no Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick, no Separatiſt from the Church, no Donatiſt, no Infant, though of Believing Parents, that dies unbaptized, can be sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved. I muſt confeſs here I am not of the mind with this Father. And, as I apprehend, that <hi>Juſtine Martyr,</hi> and ſome ſuch Anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents, who were Philoſophers as well as Chriſtians, have ſpoken more nobly than thus: So do I think that he goes not here the way of the Scriptures. There is the <hi>univerſal</hi> Grace of God; and <hi>ſpecial</hi> Grace of God, I count, held forth therein: and both conſiſtent with one another. When Chriſt ſayes, He came to ſave the <hi>World,</hi> that The Father ſo loved the <hi>World,</hi> as to give his Son, That he <hi>taſted Death for every Man,</hi> and the like; let not any think, but the Grace of <hi>Redemption</hi> doth concern all the World: And when we yet maintain <hi>ſpecial</hi> Grace with this, let not any confine the ſame to this or that Sort or Sect of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, but let him judge rather, that the Elect are ſcattered throughout the Earth; and it is <hi>God</hi> alone <hi>knows who are his.</hi> There is the univerſal Grace of <hi>Origen,</hi> that all at laſt ſhall be ſaved, of <hi>Pelagius,</hi> of <hi>Arminius.</hi> There is alſo <hi>gratia univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalis aqualis &amp; praecedanea,</hi> of <hi>John Camero;</hi> we are not bound to maintain either of theſe: but there is <hi>Gratia univerſalis ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliciter,</hi> which if we maintain not, we muſt leave our Preaching, and the Goſpel. The Followers of Truth and Mediocrity will be afraid to hold any other <hi>univerſal</hi> Grace, but ſuch as I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe St. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> holds in his Books, <hi>De vocatione Gentium;</hi> that will agree well with the <hi>ſpecial</hi> Grace alſo and <hi>Election</hi> of St. <hi>Auguſtine;</hi> that is, ſuch only, I count, as may juſtly lay the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:56460:14"/>blame of mans Sin and his Deſtruction, altogether on him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, when it gives the whole Glory of his Salvation unto God. <hi>They that obſerve lying vanityes, for ſake their own mercy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For my proceeding on this point, it is not ſutable to my pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to be critical upon any words in the original Languages that <hi>Redemption</hi> is expreſſed by: or, to pretend to curioſity in the Laws and Cuſtoms of the Jews or other nations about <hi>Redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> at large, which might be alluded to: I will rather leave this Note in my way, that, as the curious oftentimes are leaſt apt for plain things, ſo muſt I ſay, that whatſoever notion is offered upon this or any other head of Divinity by any, who perhaps are of more exquiſite learning and ſearch in ſome things than others are, if when they are ſufficiently declared, they are not apprehenſible by common and ordinary people as well as them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, I do account them little worth in the Chriſtina Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. They were plain men who at firſt Preached the Goſpel, and they were plain men for whoſe ſake it was Preached, and is Written. When I ſee evidently that there muſt goe more skill to the finding ſuch or ſuch things out, more learning, ſubtil diſtinction, and wit, that, I beleeve, any of the Apoſtles if they were living ever had, I cannot but think preſently, There is none of Chriſts diſciples would have delivered this, and it matters not my ſalvation whether it be ſo or not.</p>
               <p>Neither do I entend a <hi>Common place</hi> upon this, or other of the Heads which I treat on, but an <hi>Exercitation</hi> onely, in order to my particular deſign: you muſt not expect any more. There is one thing then I account here to be mainly of neceſſity or moment; and that is, the underſtanding our Redemption by Jeſus Chriſt but ſo, as that we may be ſolidly able to fix upon what that is which indeed accrewes to man from it, or which we may avouch for the <hi>immediate</hi> and uncontrolable fruit, or <hi>benefit,</hi> to us by it. I will not therefore make many words. The Redemption of man by Chriſt, I humbly conceive, does lye chiefly in this, The deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very of him from the <hi>Law</hi> as it was a <hi>Covenant of works,</hi> that is requiring of him ſuch conditions as he is not now in his <hi>faln eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate</hi> ever able to perform; and ſo muſt inevitably periſh, if he were not delivered from it. <hi>When the fulneſs of time was come</hi> (ſayes the Apoſtle) <hi>God ſent his Son, made under the Law.</hi> &amp;c. The
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:56460:15"/>
                  <hi>Law</hi> as given to the Jews was a <hi>repreſentative</hi> of the <hi>Law of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> or <hi>Covenant of Works:</hi> and in Chriſts redeeming the <hi>Jewes</hi> from it as given by Moſes, he does redeem the <hi>World</hi> from that covenant which it repreſented, and there, I ſay, does lye the cheif point of our Redemption. That very thing then, or that great <hi>immediate</hi> effect or benefit which accrewes to man from Chriſts dying for him, is his having other terms procured upon which he may be juſtified and ſaved, than thoſe which by the Covenant of <hi>nature</hi> were due from him to obtain that end. <hi>For, God ſo loved the World that he gave his onely begotten ſon that whoſoever beleeveth in him ſhould not periſh but have everlaſting life.</hi> What is the <hi>immediate end</hi> here of God's giving his Son, That muſt be the <hi>Immediate fruit</hi> of Chriſts coming, dying, and redeeming the World. And what is that, but that <hi>Whoſoever beleeveth in him, may not periſh?</hi> That is, The delivery of him from the law of <hi>Works,</hi> and bringing him under the Covenant or law of <hi>Faith,</hi> that, upon the performance only hereof (who could not have it elſe without <hi>perfect doing</hi>) he may obtain everlaſting life. And whether this favour of Chriſts procuring new terms upon which man may be ſaved does belong to the Elect only, or to all the world, there will need no more but to ask, To whom the Goſpel is to be preached, to decide that queſtion.</p>
               <p>It is true, that the freedom of the Jewes from the Moſaical law; the breaking down the partition-wall thereby for the Gentiles to be incorporated into one Church viſible; and a power in Chriſt himſelf to diſpenſe all aſſiſtances neceſſary to both for their obedience to the Goſpel; as alſo a diſcharge of mankind from damnation for Adams ſin onely, are fruits of Chriſts death, which may be ſaid too, immediate and univerſal: but the great benefit which indeed comprehends theſe and the like in it, and appeares ſo notorious in the whole New Teſtament, is, The re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation of the world unto God by his death or Redemption. And what elſe ſuch a reconciliation can eminently conſiſtin, but that I have named, I leave to the underſtanding to give judgment.</p>
               <p>Neither are we to forget that our Redemption in Scripture is ſaid to be from <hi>Sin,</hi> and the <hi>Devil,</hi> as well as from the <hi>Law;</hi> for the one is the Foundation of the other. When man fell from God, the Devil obtained a right and dominion over him.
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:56460:15"/>This was not a right as Lord, and Proprietour, but as Goaler and Executioner; that is, by vertue of that ſentence which the Law as the Covenant of works paſſed on him. When Chriſt then by his Satisfaction to the Juſtice of God, did put an end to that Covenant; this Right which the Devil held thereby, muſt ceaſe with it. In the Ceſſation of this Right; As the Slave who is redeemed from his ſlavery, is redeemed alſo from the work which he lives in as a Slave: So muſt all Mankind be redeemed from ſin; only this Redemption muſt be diſtinguiſhed, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of <hi>Title,</hi> and in regard of <hi>Poſſeſſion.</hi> It follows not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <hi>the World lies in Wickedneſs,</hi> and <hi>the Prince of the Air</hi> ſtill <hi>rules in the Children of Diſobedience;</hi> that Chriſt hath not done His part in their Redemption: No, while the Law which held them under an impoſſible Duty (that is, the Law of Sin and Condemnation) is taken off, and the New Law is ſuch, as e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one is capable to perform the Terms of it, if he will: It is not for want of <hi>Right</hi> to come out of this ſlavery; it is not for want of <hi>Power;</hi> but it is becauſe they are not willing to come out of it, becauſe they love their ſins; that the Devil keeps them ſtill in Poſſeſſion. Even as the <hi>Hebrew</hi> Servant, when the <hi>Jubile</hi> came; if he ſaid, he loved his Maſter, and would not go out free, he was to have his Ears boared to the Door-poſts of the Houſe, and remain his Slave for ever. There is a double work, therefore, Chriſt has to do as our Lord-Redeemer. The one is to procure Deliverance if we are willing; that is, our Redemption in regard of <hi>Title:</hi> And the other is, To make us <hi>Willing,</hi> which is, to put us alſo in Poſſeſſion. The one of theſe is that which is properly the work of our Redemption, and Univerſal: The other is peculiar to the Elect, and hath another name in Scripture; that is, our <hi>Vocation, Effectual Calling,</hi> or <hi>Converſion.</hi> Unleſs when this Poſſeſſion comes to be perfectly compleat, that is, at Death; and then it is again called the <hi>Day of Redemption.</hi> Whom he did <hi>predeſtinate</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>them he alſo called; and whom he called, them he alſo juſtified: And whom he juſtified, them he alſo glorified.</hi> If Redemption were not of a larger extent than Election, Vocation, Juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and Glory, then would the Apoſtle have ſaid; <hi>Whom he did predeſtinate, he redeemed: And whom he redeemed, he called.</hi>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:56460:16"/>But when we find no ſuch Link in this Chain, it is a convincing Argument to my underſtanding, for the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſalitie</hi> of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption.</p>
               <p>It is ſaid of Chriſt, that he is the Saviour of the world; eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially of his own body. In that Sentence we have both <hi>univerſal</hi> and <hi>ſpecial</hi> Grace together; and the one is Applicatory, not Deſtructive to the other. The <hi>Redemption</hi> of Chriſt is <hi>univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal:</hi> The Grace whereby a Man ſavingly <hi>believes,</hi> and <hi>repents,</hi> and ſo becomes one of his Body, is <hi>ſpecial,</hi> and belongs to <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection.</hi> The Death of Chriſt may be conſidered, as it redounds to the purchaſing Remiſſion of Sin and Salvation upon conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; or, as it redounds to the purchaſing the Condition for Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion and Salvation. In the firſt ſenſe, Chriſts Redemption and Grace of the Goſpel is univerſal; Doctor <hi>Twiſſe,</hi> and the like Divines, will ſay twenty times over: In the ſecond ſenſe, they will have it for his Elect only. For my own part, I muſt go from them here, and account, That the work of Chriſts Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption and whole Mediation upon Earth, does terminate in the former conſideration. The buſineſs of a Mediatour be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween parties, does lie in this, To bring them to ſome New terms, wherein they may be agreed when they were at odds before. The buſineſs of Chriſts <hi>Mediation, Redemption, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation, Propitiation, Satisfaction;</hi> or whatſoever word out of Scripture, or Orthodox Writers is uſed, does lie, I ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, in this altogether, That he hath taken that courſe with the Father, that he ſhall not deal with the world according to the Covenant of our Creation; which requires ſuch terms, as no Man now thereby can be juſtified or ſaved; but according to the Covenant of Grace, which is ſuch, that whoſoever he be, that truſting in his Mercy and Goodneſs through Chriſt, does re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, and walk <hi>ſincerely</hi> before him; though <hi>imperfectly,</hi> ſhall be Pardoned, Accepted, and Saved, and yet he be Righteous in ſo doing. This I ſay, is the <hi>res ipſa,</hi> (as I take it) <hi>the thing it ſelf,</hi> intended in all theſe ſorts of words, with the <hi>connotati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> only of the <hi>modus</hi> alſo, the <hi>mode</hi> or <hi>qualification</hi> thereof, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to ſuch ſeveral Expreſſions.</p>
               <p>Here then appears a Truth (as it ſeems at leaſt) very agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to my Reaſon; and will be found as Conſonant perhaps to
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:56460:16"/>the Judicious, with the Scripture; that the Merit, or Purchaſe of Chriſt's Death, or the Price he laid down for our Redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, was not offered to the Father, to procure of Him, that he ſhould give Faith and Repentance to any; but that he ſhould give Remiſſion to thoſe that Repent, and Salvation to thoſe that believe on him. I humbly offer you theſe Reaſons:
<list>
                     <item>1. The holding otherwiſe than thus, does make Chriſt's Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption a <hi>double thing;</hi> one thing for one man, and another thing for another: If ſhall be procuring Salvation for <hi>Judas,</hi> if he repent; and it ſhall be the procuring Repentance for <hi>Peter,</hi> that he may be ſaved.</item>
                     <item>2. It goes quite againſt the hair to reaſon, that Chriſt ſhould procure the Benefit upon Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and only on Condition, and not otherwiſe; and yet that he ſhould procure alſo the Performance. To what purpoſe do we make ſuch a Labour about as this? Why do you not ſay, He purchaſed the Benefit rather free altogether without condition?</item>
                     <item>3. If our Believing, and Repenting, be alſo purchaſed, then is there nothing in Man's Salvation but of Purchaſe; and we ſhall be beholding to <hi>Chriſt</hi> for all, and to <hi>God</hi> for nothing. But if we are beholding to Chriſt for his Purchaſe, that Salvation may be had if we repent, and to God for this Repenting; then do we ſee, how highly Both are to be magnified for the Contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance.</item>
                     <item>4. The Death and Redemption of Chriſt is for <hi>All,</hi> for <hi>every man;</hi> for <hi>our ſins,</hi> for the <hi>world's.</hi> Diſtinctions to anſwer this, are but Evaſions. But if Faith and Repentance be the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe of Chriſts Death or Redemption, then cannot his Death and Redemption be univerſal, according to ſo many Scriptures. Let me double this, and add alſo, that the Purchaſe, or Redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Chriſt being univerſal certainly, as it is in Scripture, if by his Death he had procured the Condition, as well as the Covenant, and abatement of Terms, then muſt all Men Actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally have been ſaved. I have one Reaſon yet more to offer; which is. That the want of knowing this, is I take it, the great Stumbling-block, or Temptation to our Divines, in the recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving <hi>univerſal</hi> Grace, to caſt <hi>ſpecial</hi> Grace quite off; when they ſhould learn the true Mediocrity of reconciling both theſe toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, according to the Scriptures.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>When the <hi>Arminian</hi> then argues here, Chriſt hath died for
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:56460:17"/>All and Every man and that is not to be put off with the <hi>genera ſingulorum,</hi> or, the Gentiles as well as the Jewes: therefore the grace of God is univerſal for all and every one to repent and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve that they may be ſaved. I anſwer, this is manifeſtly inconſequent, becauſe it is true that what Chriſt hath done by way of <hi>Redemption</hi> is univerſal, and belongs to all the World, and every man alike, which is terminated in procuring theſe terms to be offered to the World for ſalvation. But as for mans belief, repentance, ſincere obedience, which are the terms, they come <hi>directly</hi> and <hi>immediately</hi> otherwiſe, not from the grace of <hi>Redemption,</hi> nor from the fountain of mans <hi>free will</hi> with them, but from the grace of <hi>Election.</hi> God gives us his <hi>Son,</hi> and he gives us his <hi>Spirit.</hi> His ſending his Son is <hi>one</hi> thing, and his ſending his Spirit <hi>another.</hi> The work of <hi>drawing</hi> perſons <hi>to Chriſt,</hi> I do obſerve, is attributed to the <hi>Father</hi> and the <hi>Spirit,</hi> becauſe this is <hi>Peculiar:</hi> when the work which is attributed to Chriſt in diſtinction to them, is <hi>Generall</hi> to all mankind. He ſent his <hi>Son</hi> to purchaſe ſalvation, if we Beleeve: he ſends his <hi>Spirit</hi> to work that faith and repentance in us that we may be ſaved. In the one does lye the myſtery of our <hi>Redemption,</hi> in the other, I ſay, the myſtery of <hi>Election.</hi> Let it be true on one hand that Chriſt by his Redemption hath indeed procured no more for <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Peter,</hi> than for <hi>Judas</hi> and the reprobate, and ſo the honour of his <hi>Redemption</hi> be kept up with the <hi>Arminian</hi> to the height they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend for it: Yet may it be true, I hope likewiſe, on the other hand, that the grace of God towards <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi> was more in giving them ſaving faith and repentance, than to <hi>Judas</hi> or the reprobate, and ſo the doctrine of <hi>Speciall Grace</hi> and <hi>Election</hi> need not neither be diſcarded.</p>
               <p>For caution, There is the <hi>Direct,</hi> and <hi>Collateral</hi> iſſue (if I may ſo ſpeak) of Chriſts merit, purchaſe or death. It is certain that the Lord Jeſus may be ſaid by his death and merit to have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured his own exaltation, and as he is become thereby the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſatour of thoſe treaſures that are in his Fathers Eection, ſo repentance or faith in a collateral way may be accounted to iſſue from thence. <hi>Whom God hath exalted</hi> to be a <hi>Prince</hi> to give <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance,</hi> as well as be a <hi>Saviour,</hi> to procure <hi>remiſſion to Iſrael.</hi> But repentance, faith perſeverance, or the condition which God
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:56460:17"/>requires of us, and not of Chriſt, in the buſineſs of our ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, does not flow to us directly from, or is no direct and imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate fruit of, his <hi>Death</hi> or <hi>Redemption.</hi> I know moreover the Scripture tells us that we are <hi>bleſſed with all ſpiritual bleſſings in him:</hi> But that may be true I hope, though ſome of thoſe bleſſings only are the purchaſe of his <hi>death,</hi> and others the effect of his <hi>Interceſſion:</hi> or ſome the fruit of his <hi>Purchaſing,</hi> others the effect of his <hi>Adminiſtring</hi> of the new Covenant.</p>
               <p>This is certain, the Spirit is the Authour of our faith, repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, all grace: but the Spirit is obtained by vertue of Chriſts interceſſion. <hi>I will pray the Father, and he will ſend the Comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</hi> I offer you one argument. The Spirit proceeds not from the <hi>Son</hi> alone but from the <hi>Father</hi> and <hi>Son.</hi> The miſſion or giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Spirit therefore cannot be the effect of our <hi>Redemption</hi> which is peculiar to the Son, and belongs to all the World: but is the fruit or off ſpring of our <hi>Election.</hi> It is true, we come in the <hi>name</hi> of Chriſt to ask his Spirit, and grace, that is, we ask it through Chriſts <hi>merits:</hi> but there is the merits of his <hi>Perſon,</hi> as well as the merits of his <hi>Death;</hi> &amp; it is one thing to be the <hi>Propi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiation for our ſins,</hi> and another to be alſo our <hi>Advocate with the Father.</hi> This is that I will pitch upon, that we are not ſo to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute all things to his <hi>Oblation,</hi> as to make any other part, or parts of his <hi>Mediator-ſhip,</hi> more then needs.</p>
               <p>There is a diſtinction the Scripture makes of Chriſt in the <hi>Fleſh</hi> and in the <hi>Spirit.</hi> He was of the ſeed of David according to the the fleſh, and declared to be the ſon of God according to the Spirit, in his Reſurrection from the dead, and in his living ever to make interceſſion for us. What he did for man in the fleſh I account he did for all mankind, for he took not on him the fleſh of David onely and the elect, but of all man-kind, or of human nature: but what he does in the Spirit, that may be peculiar (in ſome points at leaſt) onely to his elect. Hence it is, that when he tells us he <hi>Laid down his life for the World,</hi> yet <hi>I pray</hi> ſayes he <hi>not for the World, but for thoſe thou haſt given me out of the World.</hi> The prayer of Chriſt is a part of his <hi>interceſſion,</hi> which is Diſtinct from his <hi>oblation,</hi> and it is no argument from his not <hi>Praying</hi> for the World, that therefore he <hi>Died</hi> not for it. <hi>If ye being e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil know how to give good gifts unto your children, how much more
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:56460:18"/>ſhall your heavenly Father give his holy Spirit to them that ask him.</hi> God hath given his <hi>Son</hi> to thoſe that never ask him, even to the whole <hi>World:</hi> but he gives the <hi>Spirit</hi> of the Son only to his <hi>Children,</hi> even to ſuch as can cry <hi>Abba Father,</hi> when they have received it. <hi>I will pray the Father and he ſhall give you another Comforter, even the Spirit of truth, whom the World cannot receive.</hi> When he prayes not for the world, that he prayes for is the <hi>Spirit,</hi> and the Spirit which works grace in the heart whereby we are ſanctified, and perſeverance to bring us to glory, is pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar to thoſe whom God does <hi>give to Chriſt,</hi> and of whom Chriſt can ſay, <hi>For they are thine, and all mine are thine, and thine are mine, and I am glorified in them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>You may ſay, on the <hi>one</hi> hand, If it be no more which Chriſt hath purchaſed for <hi>Peter</hi> then for <hi>all,</hi> then <hi>Peter</hi> might periſh for all Chriſts <hi>Purhcaſe.</hi> I anſwer, you may ſay ſo, and without ignominy to his <hi>Redemption,</hi> provided you know alſo that the <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection</hi> of God and Chriſts <hi>Prayer</hi> will provided for <hi>Peter</hi> that further which it provides not for <hi>all,</hi> and Jeſus Chriſt when he hath made his purchaſe, is the <hi>Executor</hi> of Gods <hi>Election.</hi> On the <hi>other</hi> hand it may be ſaid, But to what purpoſe is this <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption univerſal</hi> when none but thoſe that perform the conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on are ſaved? I anſwer, it is therefore <hi>univerſal,</hi> that none of thoſe who performe the condition may <hi>miſſe</hi> of Salvation. As alſo, that though it be all one to <hi>him</hi> that does not perform the ſame, in regard of the event, as if he was not all Redeemed: Yet it is not all one as to <hi>God,</hi> and the <hi>Verity</hi> of Scripture, and his <hi>Judgment</hi> according to it. The Scripture ſayes often, Chriſt <hi>Dyed for All;</hi> and that God will <hi>Judge the World</hi> according to <hi>this Goſpel.</hi> He that <hi>belives, ſhall be ſaved, he that believeth not, ſhall be damned;</hi> the Foundation whereof is Chriſts Death, which muſt reach ſo far, as to make this good. And who knows not, that the very buſineſs of our whole Religion, does depend upon the Eſtabliſhment of the Verity of the Holy Scriptures?</p>
               <p>I muſt confeſs, I ſhould moſt willingly hearken to any, that could make Chriſts Death more Advantagious; and when his purchaſe hath procured Faith and Repentance to no body, but Remiſſion and Salvation to All, upon their Faith and Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:56460:18"/>if they are willing to ſay, that there is ſufficient Grace alſo purchaſed for the <hi>World,</hi> that all, and every one ſhould Repent and Believe, and apply that Redemption; I am indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent to the uſe of their Thoughts: But if when I rather grant a univerſal Power, ariſing from Chriſts purchaſe, not as a <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect fruite</hi> of his Death, but as a <hi>conſequential Event</hi> (N.B.) from the Abatement only of the terms; that God is not want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to any <hi>in neceſſariis,</hi> and conſequently, that all men have ſufficient <hi>Light, Spirit, Grace,</hi> or <hi>Power,</hi> to be ſaved, if they will: Yet ſo long as we cannot deny him, but he may abound <hi>in gratuitis,</hi> and to give the <hi>Will</hi> and <hi>Deed</hi> it ſelf, is more than to give <hi>Power,</hi> (as to have given to <hi>Adam</hi> the <hi>Ipſum velle,</hi> had been more, and a <hi>gratuitum</hi> wherein he might have abound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, if he had pleaſed, than in giving him only <hi>Poſſe velle</hi>) I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſee by any means, but when Chriſts <hi>Death</hi> is made <hi>univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal,</hi> the Fathers <hi>Election</hi> muſt be left ſtill, <hi>Per modum decreti ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficaciter operantis, By way of a decree effectually operating,</hi> free and abſoute, in regard to the condition of it's Application. If all men have alike the <hi>Poſſe velle, The Power to will,</hi> and no more, then muſt the reaſon, Why one man Repents, and is Saved, and not another, be reſolved into his own ſelf only, and ſo may and muſt he ſay, it is I, I my ſelf have <hi>made the difference,</hi> when the Scripture does ſay, <hi>Who is it, O man, that hath made thee to differ?</hi> But if we allow (as <hi>Redemption</hi> to be <hi>univerſal</hi> ſo) a <hi>Poſſe velle</hi> from <hi>general:</hi> (I ſay, not a <hi>Poſſe velle</hi> as to the <hi>Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant</hi> of our <hi>Creation,</hi> but as to the <hi>Terms</hi> of the <hi>Goſpel:</hi>) And to the Elect, the <hi>Ipſum velle</hi> from <hi>ſpecial</hi> Grace, we ſhall neither have any thing to <hi>charge God,</hi> nor give occaſion to <hi>Mans boaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</hi> Neither ſhall the condition be held <hi>impoſſible;</hi> nor when we have performed it, ſhall we rob God of his Glory.</p>
               <p>It is pleaded, That unleſs Faith and Repentance does lie in every Man's own Breaſt, Chriſt's purchaſe of Pardon upon that Condition, is but a Mock. I anſwer, To deny that to Believe, and to Repent, does lye in our <hi>Power,</hi> were indeed, to evacu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate Chriſt's Death to All, beſides the Elect: But to ſay, that Faith and Repentance therefore does flow from our own <hi>Wills,</hi> is another matter. I muſt offer moreover; If Chriſt had pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed Faith and Repentance for <hi>ſome</hi> which All have not, the
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:56460:19"/>Reprobate might here have ſomething to ſay, That the Reaſon why he Repented not, as the Elect did, was, becauſe Chriſt purchaſed Repentance for the <hi>One,</hi> and not for the <hi>Other:</hi> But if Chriſt hath purchaſed nothing for <hi>One,</hi> but what he hath pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed for <hi>All</hi> (which <hi>directly</hi> is true,) then cannot the purchaſe of Chriſt be a Mock to any, ſeeing ſome do reap a real Benefit by it, and if others do not, it muſt be their Own fault. Indeed thoſe Divines, who confound the Bleſſings we have in Chriſt, ſo as to make them All alike the <hi>direct</hi> Fruits of his Death with no difference, muſt be under ſome manifeſt Prejudice here againſt St. <hi>Auguſhine,</hi> and his Doctrine. It ſtands not with reaſon, that any thing which is part of Chriſt's Purchaſe, ſhould be <hi>peculiar,</hi> for how then hath Chriſt dyed for <hi>All?</hi> That which is of <hi>meer Favour,</hi> is fit for the <hi>Elect;</hi> that which is of <hi>Purchaſe,</hi> ſhould be <hi>univerſal,</hi> or for All Mankind. If that Grace then, whereby we Believe and Repent, is a Fruit flowing from Chriſt's Death, no otherwiſe than the Covenant it ſelf does, theſe Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines alone muſt ſpeak agreeably, who will allow no other, but that which they call <hi>ſufficient,</hi> putting all men into an <hi>aequi libri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um,</hi> or <hi>equal Ballance,</hi> between Chooſing and Refuſing, and ſo leaving it upon their own <hi>Wills,</hi> to <hi>make the Difference,</hi> Who are ſaved, and who are not ſaved? But to what little purpoſe ſuch <hi>Grace</hi> as this, is diſtinguiſhed at all from <hi>Nature,</hi> and into what inconveniences, eſpecially in reference to our Prayers, they muſt be lead that maintain it, I ſhall not be able to ſay preſently. <hi>Cur admonemur orare pro inimicis noſtris vtique no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lentibus pie vivere, niſi ut Deus in illis operetur &amp; velle? Item cur admonemur petere ut accipiamus, niſi &amp; ab illo fiat quod volumus, a quo factum eſt ut velimus.</hi> Again, <hi>Cur petitur quod ad noſtram pertinet poteſtatem, ſi Deus non adjuvat veluntatem? Why are we bid to Pray for our Enemies, whoſe Hearts we know are Averſe? Why are we bid to ask any thing which is in our own Power, but that it is God who turns the Will?</hi> Auguſtine. Enchir: ad Laur. c. 31. Item De Gra. &amp; alibi paſſim.</p>
               <p>It is certain, that St. <hi>Auſtine,</hi> ſpeaking of what Grace <hi>Adam</hi> had, and what <hi>We</hi> have (<hi>De correptione &amp; Gratia.</hi> c. 11.) does aſcribe the <hi>Poſſe permanere ſi vellet, The power of ſtanding if he would</hi> unto Grace. <hi>Prima gratia quae d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>a eſt Adam, eſt qua fit
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:56460:19"/>ut habeat homo juſtitiam ſi velit: Secunda ergo plus poteſt, qua etiam fit, ut velit.</hi> Again, <hi>Poſſe permanere ſi vellet, quia dederat adjutorium per quod poſſet. He could have ſtood if he would, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe God vouchſafed help whereby he could.</hi> I muſt confeſs, I ſhould have judged it not to be of <hi>Grace,</hi> that <hi>Adam</hi> had his <hi>Poſſe perſeverare, his ſtrength to perſenere,</hi> but of <hi>Nature,</hi> or his <hi>Original Righteouſneſs:</hi> And that <hi>Grace</hi> (which he calls <hi>Adju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torium</hi>) is proper to our falne Eſtate, for the <hi>relieving</hi> of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. But if it were of <hi>Grace,</hi> that <hi>Adam</hi> had the <hi>poſſe</hi> only, when he had not the <hi>velle,</hi> then may we aſſert <hi>univerſal Grace</hi> with the more Authority; while we ſay, that there is a <hi>poſſe</hi> now in Man falne, as to the performance of the <hi>Covenant of Grace,</hi> no leſs than in <hi>Adam</hi> at firſt, as to his keeping the <hi>Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant</hi> of <hi>Works:</hi> when yet the <hi>velle,</hi> which is of <hi>ſpecial Grace,</hi> is not vouchſafed.</p>
               <p>There may be here indeed, a moſt difficult Demand, and that muſt not be baulked; Whether the <hi>Power,</hi> which is <hi>uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal,</hi> be of <hi>Nature</hi> or <hi>Grace?</hi> And I muſt profeſs, it is an En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tanglement to my Thoughts, to diſtinguiſh <hi>Nature</hi> at all, from that <hi>Grace</hi> which is <hi>univerſal.</hi> Although for the ſake I ſuppoſe of ſome Texts, which attribute our <hi>ſufficiency,</hi> our <hi>can,</hi> our <hi>power,</hi> as well as our <hi>will</hi> and <hi>deed</hi> to God, when they ſay too it is not <hi>of our ſelves,</hi> Divines do it. There is that <hi>Concourſe,</hi> or <hi>Operation</hi> of God with Us, as reaches to the Endowing us with <hi>Power:</hi> or that which reaches to the Endowing us with the <hi>Will.</hi> The laſt of theſe only, if I might chooſe, I would have called <hi>Grace:</hi> Yet ſeeing Divines ſpeak otherwiſe, whether the former alſo, be called <hi>Grace</hi> or <hi>Nature,</hi> ſo long as it be held <hi>univerſal,</hi> I deſire to move no Contention. And you ſee me ſpeak as one indifferent in it.</p>
               <p>If we conſult the <hi>Schools,</hi> we ſhall find them giving as little to the ſtrengh of nature as any others can doe. <hi>Nullum initium juſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificationis poteſt fieri ſine gratia, Sive lllud initium ſit cauſa, ſive meritum, condigni aut congrui, ſive impetratio, diſpoſitio, condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio ad quodlibet aliquid, quocun<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> modo per ſe &amp; ratione ſui, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducens ad juſtificationem. There is nothing that we can doe of our own ſtrengh without grace that is any cauſe, merit, diſpoſition, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, or occaſion of our juſtification,</hi> or the <hi>beginning</hi> of it. Ruiz.
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:56460:20"/>
                  <hi>De praedeſtinationis exordio.</hi> Trac. 3. Diſp. 17. By juſtification they underſtand in effect regeneration, and they diſtinguiſh of an <hi>occaſion</hi> which is <hi>active</hi> or <hi>given of men,</hi> and <hi>paſſive</hi> or <hi>taken of God.</hi> They will allow indeed that what we doe may be a <hi>Paſſive</hi> oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion or opportunity to God for the infuſing his grace, which is with them to <hi>juſtify</hi> us, but no <hi>Active. Illae occaſiones perſe, &amp; ratione ſui, nullam Phyſican, nec moralem cauſalitatem exercent, ad ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinendam miſcriocordiam Dei, ſed Deus pro ſua intriuſcca bonitate &amp; Sapientia, ex illis occaſionem accipit.</hi> Jb. Diſt. 16 Sec. 2. The ſum is, that whatſoever man does by the ſtrengh of nature, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duces to his effectuall converſion onely (as a <hi>removens prohibens</hi>) by <hi>removing the hindrance</hi> which otherwiſe we might put, if we with drew from the <hi>means</hi> that God hath appointed to obtain his grace. <hi>Licet cuim aliquis per motum liberi arbitris divinam gratiam nec promercri nec acquirere poſſit: poteſt tamen ſeipſum im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedire ne eam recipiat,</hi> ſayes <hi>Aquinas. Though a man by the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his freewill cannot merit or procure the divine grace: yet can he hinder himſelf from receiving it.</hi> They ſaid unto God, Depart from us we deſire not the knowledg of thy ways. <hi>Quilibet ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ius qui a nobis eliciatur per vires naturae ſine anxilio gratiae nihil ad gratiam juſtificantem, nee ad auxiliatricem gratiam inſluit: nihilue conducit aut confert perſe ratione ſui, ſed ſoluwnmodo quaſi cauſa per accidens remonendo prohibens, aut tanquam occaſio &amp; opportunitas paſſiua &amp; a Deo accepta, non ab hominibus data.</hi> Jb. Diſt. 20.</p>
               <p>Having gon thus far in abaſing the ſtrengh of nature, we ſhall find how they make it up again, with advancing an <hi>univerſall. Sufficient grace,</hi> by the help of which lever the <hi>free will</hi> of man ſhall be lifted into the ſame throne, from whence before they threw it down. For when that grace which they ſet up, muſt be ſuch only as gives a <hi>next</hi> power to beleeve and repent if we will, but leaves the will undetermined and uninclined, and this being Suppoſed to be vouchſafed to all according to the condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion they are in, whether Elect or Reprobate alike, it is apparent that mans <hi>free will</hi> by the <hi>cooperation</hi> with this grace, or <hi>refuſal,</hi> is that which begins, or puts by his own juſtification, and cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently <hi>makes the differenee</hi> (in the upſhot) between him that is ſaved, and him that is damned. <hi>Supponimus omnibus adultis,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:56460:20"/>nullo excepto, dari auxilia ſufficientia ad ſalutem, &amp; non impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dita, ſed ita expedita, ut in poteſtate cujuſque ſit, illis cooperan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do, ulteriora auxilia obtinere, quanrvis per vires naturae non poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſint obtinere auxilia gratiae.</hi> Again, <hi>Barbari ignorantiſſimi per interiorem gratiam moventur ad cognoſeendum (non explicite ſed implicite &amp; virtualiter, non certo ſed ſubdubio, non in particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lari ſed in univerſali) aliquid ſupernaturale, atque ad illud de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderandum: Idque ſufficit ut illuſtrationes &amp; inſpirationes ſiut quidditative ſupernaturales &amp; ſufficientes ad juſtificationis initi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um. Idem ib Diſp.</hi> 25. Now what my thoughts are of this, I have offered as I paſs; and more particularly, at the end, upon the firſt Head, of Election. There is <hi>univerſal</hi> Grace <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent</hi> with the <hi>Special</hi> Grace of Gods Elect: Or <hi>inconſiſient</hi> with it. The former, I ſhall like to have well explained. The latter, I take to be againſt St. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> and the Scriptures. The Grace of God is <hi>without,</hi> or <hi>within</hi> us. There is the Love, or Good-will of God to Mankind, who <hi>would have All to be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved:</hi> Our Redemption by Chriſt; The remedyicg Covenant; The Goſpel. This is Grace <hi>without,</hi> and that ſome Grace there is then <hi>ſufficient,</hi> and <hi>univerſal,</hi> that yet hath no Effect on the moſt, is out of doubt. There is moreover, that Grace which lies in the Help, or Aſſiſtance of the Spirit <hi>within,</hi> and the Fruit of it <hi>(Gratia Auxiliatrix, &amp; Infuſa)</hi> and this our Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines doe diſtinguiſh into <hi>Common</hi> and <hi>Saving.</hi> By <hi>Common,</hi> they underſtand not the <hi>univerſal ſufficient Aſſiſtance</hi> of the Schools before, but ſome particular Operation of the Spirit, <hi>Effecting</hi> ſo much as it is given for, only becauſe thoſe <hi>Effects</hi> reach no farther than what is Common to the Elect and Repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate, they call ſuch <hi>Help</hi> or <hi>Grace</hi> only <hi>Common Grace.</hi> Thus far we are ſafe; As for any Grace beſides all this, if there be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, not oppoſing Electing Grace, I ſhall be glad to hear it; but my own mind, I perceive, hangs thus. There is a Power to <hi>will</hi> or <hi>nill,</hi> to <hi>act</hi> or <hi>not to act,</hi> which is the power of Nature: And there is a <hi>Diſpoſition</hi> on the Will, being touched by the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Spirit, to the doing what is good. Between theſe two, <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> and <hi>Grace,</hi> to advance a middle Power, ariſing from an Aſſiſtance <hi>ſufficient,</hi> preceding <hi>Effectual,</hi> that is to ſay, To make God by a <hi>ſupernatural</hi> Help, to produce a New Power,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:56460:21"/>which they call, a <hi>next</hi> Power, in every man, over and above that Power which we have by <hi>Nature</hi> (which is the <hi>Remote</hi> Power, though the Schools mean it not ſo, and which alone will render the Sinner inexcuſable without any other) antece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent to the giving the <hi>Will</hi> and the <hi>Deed,</hi> wherein <hi>effectual</hi> Grace does lie: Even a New Power, I ſay, <hi>Supernatural,</hi> of Believing, Repenting, or Willing, beſides the <hi>Natural,</hi> antecedent to Faith, Repentance, or the Will it ſelf: I do not ſee to what pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe elſe, if it be not a Device under the Cover of that Name, to advance <hi>Free-will,</hi> and flap off St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> (as I take it to be in the Schooles) it can be made to ſerve. What need is there of <hi>Grace,</hi> to put the Will only in <hi>aequilibrio,</hi> which it is in by <hi>Nature?</hi> If it <hi>encines</hi> not the <hi>Will,</hi> and carries the <hi>Heart</hi> and <hi>Life:</hi> What ſhall I ſay of it, but as of the <hi>Wood</hi> of the <hi>Vine? Is it meet for any Work?</hi> Yet if it be, I refuſe not to hang my Veſſel on it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Auxilium, aliud eſt proxime &amp; immediate ſufficiens, quod vide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licet formaliter &amp; actualiter continet omnes cauſas, &amp; conditiones, ex parte principii requiſitas ad eliciendum actum quo immediate diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>umur ad juſtificationem: Aliud vero non ſufficit ad ſalutem niſi mediate atque remote, quatenus immediate ſufficiens eſt ad eliciend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um aliquem actum ſupernaturalem minus perfectum &amp; remote di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantem a juſtificatione; quem actum ſi peccator eliciat, de con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gruo merebitur, &amp; impetrabit vlteriora auxilia ſupernaturalia, quibus poſſit elicere Perfectiores actus, proximius diſponentes ad juſtificationem, quouſque ipſam obtineat.</hi> Ruiz. De praecip. effec. benevol. Dei erga reprob. Sec. 2. <hi>Auxilium vel immediate vel mediate ſufficiens, omnibus adultis, quamdiu ſunt viatores, tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buitur ad omnes actiones quae ſunt ad ſalutem ſimpliciter neceſſariae.</hi> Ib. Sec. 3. <hi>Auxilium remotum ſimpliciter neceſſarium cujus vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute fit abſolute poſſibile proximum Auxilium obtinere, nunquam ſubtrahitur, etiam, propter graviſſimas culpas.</hi> De prin. imped. juſtif. Sec. 5. I preſent this to the Reader only for Light, out of courteſie, that he who would without more pains, may yet ſee, how the Schools order their Matters. And the truth is, if they would <hi>order</hi> it but a <hi>little</hi> otherwiſe, without it's Ante<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedency and Equality, This <hi>ſufficient univerſal Grace</hi> of theirs might do well. There is an Equality in regard of <hi>Quantity,</hi>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:56460:21"/>which no body will contend for: Or in regard of <hi>Principle, Ratione principii in actu primo cauſantis Operationem.</hi> The con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of God, as the firſt cauſe, with Nature in all her Acts, and ſo with Mans Free-will, is one <hi>principle of Operation:</hi> And that Aſſiſtance which we call <hi>Grace,</hi> is another. Of <hi>Grace</hi> likewiſe, the Aſſiſtance which is <hi>Common,</hi> and which is <hi>Effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al,</hi> are two <hi>Principles</hi> according to us. If we ſhall therefore make the Aſſiſtance of God, which belongs to <hi>all,</hi> to be <hi>equal,</hi> we deſtroy <hi>ſpecial</hi> Grace: But if we ſeperate this Equality from the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſality,</hi> and tye not an Antecedency to the <hi>ſufficiency</hi> (for what hinders, but God may work <hi>effectually</hi> on ſome Perſons altogether graceleſs at once?) I ſee no hurt in the <hi>Maintenance</hi> of it, if I were firſt convinced of a <hi>neceſſity</hi> for it.</p>
               <p>From hence there is a Point of another ſort, that is, of Practical Divinity comes in upon us: To wit, How far a Natural Man may go, and yet fall ſhort of True Grace, and Salvation? To anſwer which, we are to know, that it is one thing to ask what a Natural man <hi>can do?</hi> And another, What he may do, and yet be an Unre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate Man? The firſt Queſtion, is the Controverſal Point in hand, between Us and the <hi>Arminians:</hi> And I ſay, it is agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to that <hi>Righteouſneſs of God,</hi> which is Revealed in the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, and to Common Reaſon, that when Chriſt dyed to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deem the World from the Law of Works, becauſe through the Weakneſs of the Fleſh, it was impoſſible for us to perform the ſame; the New Terms which he hath procured for us in the Remedying Law, ſhould be ſo Adapted to our Falne E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, as to be made no leſs poſſible to us, or within our Power now, than the Terms of the Covenant of Nature, was to <hi>Adam</hi> in the ſtate of Innocency. There is no Interpretation of any Scripture, muſt be admitted againſt univerſal Reaſon, and the goodneſs of God. For the ſecond Queſtion: Take a Drunkard, or the like Sinner, I ſay, this man can, and may preſently re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve to keep his ill Company no more; he may command his outward Man, and ſo his leggs to carry him from the Ale-houſe, if he will. If he does thus, he leaves that ſin, ſo may he o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. He may Hear, Pray, ſet up Duty in his Family: He may <hi>Receive the Word,</hi> which is more, and bring forth <hi>Fruit,</hi>
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:56460:22"/>with this difference only, that the Regenerate man, does it with an <hi>honeſt Heart,</hi> which he hath not. There is the <hi>matter</hi> of our Duty, and the <hi>manner</hi> of <hi>Performance.</hi> This Queſtion which ſeems ſo difficult, perhaps to many, is eaſily determined. The Unregenerate man <hi>can</hi> do if he will, and may <hi>will,</hi> and <hi>do,</hi> that, and all that which the Regenerate man does, in the <hi>mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter:</hi> but as for the <hi>manner,</hi> this is certain, that the Regenerate man, only does act out of that <hi>Principle,</hi> and to that <hi>End,</hi> and with thoſe <hi>Circumſtances</hi> (particularly, in regard to the Predo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minancy of Gods Intereſt, over the Fleſh and we World) as brings up what he does, to anſwer the Covenant Terms, and ſo alone is entituled to the promiſed Reward, which is to be juſtified and ſaved. In concluſion, we ſee how the Miſtery of Election ſhews it ſelf; when there is no man but <hi>can,</hi> if he will, and yet there is no man ever <hi>will,</hi> as he ought, without this <hi>ſpecial</hi> Grace of the Elect; What ſhall we ſay, but, <hi>Great is the myſtery of Godlineſs!</hi> It is <hi>he hath wrought us for this ſelf ſame thing;</hi> Bleſſed be the God of Grace!</p>
               <p>And here are there ſome <hi>Socinian,</hi> as well as <hi>Arminian</hi> Diſputes might be Touched, under this Head of Chriſt's <hi>Redemption,</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially in relation to his <hi>Satisfaction.</hi> For it may be, that ſuch a leſs intricate Conception only of what we are to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand by Chriſt's <hi>Satisfaction,</hi> might bring the moſt of ſeveral Parties of Agreement. It is a Queſtion, Whether God could pardon a Sinner without Satisfaction? And conſequently, Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther there be any neceſſity of Chriſt's Dying to that purpoſe? I anſwer, There is no Mortal, upon the Terms of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of our Creation, can be juſtified. (Hence is it <hi>(N. B.)</hi> that by <hi>Nature,</hi> we are all ſaid to be the <hi>Children of Wrath,</hi>) It is neceſſary therefore, theſe Terms be altered. This is that which Jeſus Chriſt hath procured for Us by His <hi>Redemption,</hi> by the <hi>Merits</hi> of his <hi>Life</hi> and <hi>Death,</hi> by his <hi>Satisfaction;</hi> that is, ſuch a well-pleaſing of the Father, in the whole courſe of his Life and Death, that for his ſake, he <hi>might</hi> (without any Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honour to him, or to his Law, as Rector) and <hi>does</hi> condeſcend to do it: And there ſhould be an end, if I might over-rule the more Intelligent, of ſuch, and the like kind of Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
            </div>
            <closer>
               <signed>Deo Gloria, mihi Condonatio. <hi>J. H.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:56460:22"/>
            <head>An Advertiſement.</head>
            <p>THis Paper <hi>Of Election and Redemption,</hi> ſhould have preceded the former <hi>Of Juſtification</hi> the Term be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. The next in order, <hi>Of the Law and the Goſpel, and the Covenants of both,</hi> will follow (if prudence direct) the Term enſuing. Sold, and to be Sold by the ſame Book<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellers, <hi>T.P.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
